<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->
<section xml:id="activity-domain-range" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Domain and Range Activity </title>
  <subsection>
      <title>Domain and Range</title>
      
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li><p>What kinds of input does a function accept?</p></li>
          <li><p>Once a function is given an input value, what are all the possible outputs you can get?</p></li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>In math we have our own vocabulary we use to ask the same questions.  The kinds of inputs a function will accept is called the <term>domain</term> of the function.  All the possible outcomes is call the <term>range</term>.</p>
      <example>
        <p>Consider online shopping at a t-shirt store.  Each t-shirt costs $13.00 and each time you click on the <q>add to shopping cart</q> your account adds a charge for $13.00.  In this case the cost C of shopping is a function of the number N of t-shirts you add to the cart.  Therefore, <m>C = f(N)</m>.</p>
        <p>What kinds of values for N does our function accept?</p>
        <p>Well, you can't choose to buy negative t-shirts so N can't be less than zero.  You can buy 0 t-shirts or 1 or 2 or more, but you can't buy 1.5 t-shirts or 2.63 t-shirts.  You can only buy whole t-shirts, not fractions of shirts.</p>
        <p>In math we say that the domain of our function is <em>non-negative integers</em>.  This means the domain is the numbers N = 0, 1, 2, 3, <init>etc.</init> these are the only numbers that make sense for our function, the only numbers our function accepts.</p>
        <p>What are all the possible output values of our function?</p>
        <p>Let's see, if you don't click to add t-shirts, then <m>N = 0</m>, your cart will have no t-shirst and you won't pay anything, <m>f(0) = 0</m>.</p>
        <p>If you choose <m>N = 1</m> t-shirts you will pay $13.00  At <m>N = 2</m> you pay $26.00</p>
        <p>Notice you can't pay a negative amount.  The least cost you will ever get is $0.00 for <m>N = 0</m> t-shirts. Also notice you will never have a final checkout of $10.00 or $18.00, in fact, you will only pay in multiples of $13.00 because, again, you can't buy fractions of a t-shirt.</p>
        <p>In math we say the <term>range</term> of our function is <em>all non-negative integer multiples of <m>13</m></em>.</p>
      </example>
      
      <todo>Jack, make a webwork problem out the content below</todo>

      <p>Sometimes a function can use any number as an input.</p>
      <p>Consider <me>f(x) = x^2</me> Can you think of a number you can't multiply by itself? <em>Hint: No, you can multiply any number by itself and you will always get a result.</em> Therefore, the domain of <m>f(x) = x^2</m> is <q>all real numbers</q></p>
      <p>Sometimes a function is only defined for certain kinds of values.</p>
      <p>Consider <me>f(x) = \sqrt{x}</me> This function will yield real number results as long as the input is not negative. In this case the function has a domain <m>x \geqslant 0</m>.</p>
      <p>Similarly, the range of a function could be <q>all real numbers</q> or maybe there are only specific values the function will ever produce.</p>
      <p>In this activity we observe the domain and range of a fucntion graphically then in tables and finally in formulas.</p>

      <p>Checkout the graph of <m>f</m> shown in the exercise below. Use the slider to adust the domain of the function and see how it affects the range.</p>

          <exercise>
              <webwork>
                  <setup>
                      <var name="$variablename">
                          <static>10</static>
                      </var>

                      <pg-code>
                          $variablename = Real(10);
                      </pg-code>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/TdQ8ajW3/width/413/height/270/border/888888" width="413px" height="270px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                    <p>Need to insert values on vertical and horizontal axes to properly identify the ends of the intervals.</p>

                    <p><var name="$variablename" width="5" /></p>
                </statement>
              </webwork>
          </exercise>
  </subsection>
</section>
