<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->

<section xml:id="activity-functions-function-notation" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Function Notation (Input, Output) Activity</title>

    <objectives>
        <title>Student Learning Outcomes</title>
        <introduction>
            <p>After completing this activity you will be able to:</p>
        </introduction>
        <ol>
            <li>
                <p>Interpret the meaning of function notation.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>Use function notation to describe an event.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>Evaluate a function and solve an equation using function notation.</p>
            </li>
        </ol>
    </objectives>

    <introduction>
        <p>In this activity we define a function and develop an understanding of function notation by comparing statements we already understand in English to equivalent statements written in <q>math</q> language.</p>

        <p>The prerequisites for this lesson are knowing how to read a graph or a table of values and how to use a formula to make a calculation.</p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <title>What is a Function?</title>

        <p>The mathematical concept of a function can be extremely complicated. It took thousands of years to come up with it, define it and formalize it. For example, just look at this definition from <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Function_(mathematics)">Wikipedia</url> (do not spend too much time on it.)</p>
        <p>You could spend your whole life learning about what a function is and never get to the rest of this book! For this reason we will keep things simple and informal in order to attain a quick and accessible understanding of topics, including functions. Students continuing in mathematics will add to their knowledge of fucntions as needed and as part of a life-long process.</p>

        <p>Start by remebmering this: one input, one output.</p>

        <p>A <term>function</term><index><main>function</main></index> is a rule that takes a piece of <q>usable</q> information that you choose (input) and gives you some kind of result (output).  By <q>usable</q> we mean information that has meaning for the function.</p>
        <p>Think of a function as a sort of machine.  Using some input, the machine does something to the input and then out pops a result.  In this course our inputs will be mostly numbers and the process will yeild numbers as results.</p>
         <exercise>
            <introduction><p>A simple example of a function is a temperature converter. It converts a temperature from degrees Fahrenheit to degrees Celsius.</p>
            <p>The function is the rule or process used to convert from one unit of temperature to the other.</p>
            </introduction>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$evaluate">
                        <static>25</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$solve">
                        <static>F=-7.6</static>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        for my $i (0,1) {
                            $gr[$i] = init_graph(-60,-60,110,110,axes=>[0,0],grid=>[17,17],size=>[400,400]);
                            $gr[$i]->lb('reset');
                            for my $j (-40,-20,20,40,60,80,100) {
                                $gr[$i]->moveTo($j,-3);
                                $gr[$i]->lineTo($j,3,'black',3);
                                $gr[$i]->lb(new Label($j,-3,$j,'black','center','top'));
                                $gr[$i]->moveTo(-5,$j);
                                $gr[$i]->lineTo(5,$j,'black',3);
                                $gr[$i]->lb(new Label(7,$j,$j,'black','left','middle'));
                            };
                            $gr[$i]->lb(new Label(105,5,'Temp (deg F)','black','right','bottom'));
                            $gr[$i]->lb(new Label(5,105,'Temp (deg C)','black','left','middle'));
                            add_functions($gr[$i], "5/9*(x-32) for x in &lt;-160,110> using color:blue and weight:2");
                        };
                        $gr[1]->moveTo(77,0);
                        $gr[1]->lineTo(77,25,'black',1);
                        $gr[1]->arrowTo(0,25,'black',1);
                        $gr[1]->moveTo(0,-22);
                        $gr[1]->lineTo(-7.6,-22,'black',1);
                        $gr[1]->arrowTo(-7.6,0,'black',1);
                        Context()->flags->set(tolType=>'absolute',tolerance=>'3');
                        $evaluate=Compute("25");
                        Context("Numeric");
                        Context()->flags->set(tolType=>'absolute',tolerance=>'3');
                        Context()->variables->are(C=>'Real',F=>'Real');
                        parser::Assignment->Allow;
                        $solve=Formula("F=-7.6");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                  <p>Our function is a graph, but it could have been a table of values or a formula.</p>
                  <p>The graph illustrates that the temperature in degress Celsius is a <term>function</term> of the temperature in degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
                    <p>The temperature in degrees Fahrenheit, <m>F</m>, is the input while the temperature in degrees Celsius, <m>C</m>, is the output.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <image pg-name="$gr[0]" />
                    </figure>
                    <p>Use the graph to estimate your answers below:<ol>
                        <li>
                            <p>The temperature of <m>77</m> degrees Fahrenheit to degrees Celsius</p>
                            <p><m>C=</m> <var name="$evaluate" width="15" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>What temperature in Fahrenheit is the same as <m>-22</m> degrees Celsius? (Type your answer as <q><m>F=\ldots</m></q>.)</p>
                            <p><var name="$solve" width="15" /></p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                </statement>
                <solution>
                    <p>To graphically find these answers, visualize arrows and guidelines on the graph. To find the Celsius equivalent of <m>77</m> degrees Fahrenheit, recognize that <m>77</m> is an input value, and so you must identify it on the horizontal axis. From there, move up, then left to the vertical axis, where you land at about <m>25</m> degrees Celsius. So <m>77 \text{degrees Fahrenheit} \approx25 \text{degrees Celsius}</m>.</p>

                    <figure>
                        <image pg-name="$gr[1]" />
                    </figure>

                    <p>A similar process in reverse is used to determine the Fahrenheit temperature equivalent of <m>-22</m> degrees Celsius. Recognize that <m>-22</m> is an output, and so you must identify it on the vertical axis. From there, move left, then up to the horizontal axis, where you land at about <m>-8</m> degrees Fahrenheit. So the answer is <m>F\approx-8</m>.</p>
                </solution>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
        <p>This brings up some good questions:</p>
        <p><ul>
              <li><p>How do we communicate that we have a function? There has to be a simple or quick way to communicate we have a function.</p></li>
              <li><p>What kinds of inputs can the function use? The temperature function in the previous exercise could only accept temperatures between <m>-60</m> and <m>110</m> degrees Fahrenheit.  The input of <m>150</m> degrees <m>F</m> is not usable because it is not available to choose.</p></li>
              <li><p>What are the possible output temperatures in degrees Celsius?  Is any temperature possible or is there a window of reasonable temperature expectations?</p></li>
              <li><p>How are the two temperature units related? If you increase degrees F, does the temperture in degrees <m>C</m> also increase?</p></li>
            </ul>
          </p>
        <p>We start with notation. We don't want to keep writing the word, F U N C T I O N, all the time. That's just way too many letters.</p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Math as a Language</title>

        <p>Math is just another language. We use it to communicate measurements, changes in value and how things are related to or affect one another. Almost everything you say or describe in Math, you can say or describe in English.</p>

        <p>In this next exercise we learn to communicate the position of a train as time passes and develop the notation to express where the train is at different times. We will assume that this train runs on time, every day and the conditions every day are the same. You know, an alternate universe called <q>example land</q>.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork seed="1">
                <setup>
                    <var name="$time">
                        <static>2</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$position">
                        <static>30</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$units">
                        <set>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{miles}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours}</member>
                             <member>\text{miles per hour}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours per mile}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $time = Real(random(2,7,1));
                        if($envir{problemSeed}==1){$time=2;};
                        $position = Real(40*exp(2.6*($time-2))/(1+exp(2.6*($time-2)))+10);
                        $units = PopUp(["?", "miles", "hours", "miles per hour", "hours per mile"], "miles");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Consider the graph below.</p>

                    <p>The dot on the graph represents the position of a train at a particular time. The crosshairs represent the time.</p>

                    <p>Adjust the time by sliding crosshairs left and right.  Notice that the train's distance, in miles, from downtown depends on the time, in hours, after 8 a.m.</p>

                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/D4s2v4ft/width/450/height/459/border/888888/rc/false/ai/false/sdz/false/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/true/ld/false/sri/false/at/auto" width="450px" height="459px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                    <p>How far from downtown is the train <m><var name="$time" /></m> hours after 8 a.m.?</p>

                    <p><var name="$position" width="5" /> <var name="$units" form="popup" /></p>

                    <p>Without knowing anything about function notation, you can still use a language you already know, English, to describe information about the train.</p>

                    <p>For instance:<ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>The train can only be in one place at any particular time.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>As time passes the train gets farther from downtown.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>The speed of the train changes during its trip.</p>
                        </li>
                    </ul></p>

                    <p>There are also some characteristics of the graph itself you can also describe in English:<ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>The graph rises as we read it from left to right.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Sometimes the graph is curved upwards.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Sometimes the graph curves downwards.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Some parts of the graph are steeper than others.</p>
                        </li>
                    </ul></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>In English you can communicate information about time and position in a simple sentence like</p>

        <blockquote>
            <p><m>2</m> hours after 8 <init>a.m.</init> the train is <m>30</m> miles from downtown.</p>
        </blockquote>

        <p>Here is what that same sentence looks like in Spanish.</p>

        <blockquote>
            <p><m>2</m> horas despues de las 8 de la mañana el tren esta 30 millas lejos del centro.</p>
        </blockquote>

        <p>Here is what that same sentence could look like in <q>math</q>.</p>

        <blockquote>
            <p><m>f(2) = 30</m></p>
        </blockquote>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>The Grammar of Function Notation</title>

        <p>The math <q>sentence</q> above is actually an equation and it uses <term>function notation</term><index><main>function</main><sub>notation</sub></index><index><main>notation</main><sub>for functions</sub></index> to express the information about the train's position at a particular time.</p>

        <p>In math we don't really have subjects or verbs or objects. Instead we have input values (numbers) and we have output values. The function is the <q>machine</q> or the rule that tells us how to use the input to make an output.</p>

        <p>Variables are used to represent values we don't know or that may change. The distance from downtown is constantly changing with time, so we can let <m>D</m> represent the <q>Train's distance in miles from downtown</q>.</p>
        <p>For the <q>number of hours after 8 a.m.</q>, we can use the variable <m>t</m> where t counts how many hours have passed since 8 a.m.</p>

        <p>Typically we use variables that have something to do with the context of the problem, but sometimes we generalize an expression or equation with <m>x</m>'s and <m>y</m>'s when we have nothing specific in mind.</p>
        <paragraphs>
            <title>Variables have units</title>
                <p>If the variables represent actual things or events we must define the varialbles to include the <term>units</term><index><main>units</main></index> we used to measure the event. This allows us to extract meaning from the values or expressions.</p>
                <p>If you know Spanish you can <em>interpret</em> the meaning of a Spanish article you read into English.  Likewise, if you know <q>math</q> you can interpret the meaning of function notation into English if you know what the variables in the notation mean or what they are measuring.</p>
        
                <blockquote>
                    <p>If <m>D</m> is distance you must define the units in which the distance is measured: miles, inches, centimeters, light years<ellipsis />what?</p>
                </blockquote>
        
                <blockquote>
                    <p>If <m>t</m> is time, will it be measured with units of seconds, hours<ellipsis />years?</p>
                </blockquote>
        </paragraphs>
        <p>Since the position of the train depends on the amount of time that has passed, we say <q>the distance depends on time</q>.  In fact, the distance of the train from downtown is a <term>function of time</term>.</p>

        <p>Function notation allows us to communicate that distance is a function of time by simply writing <m>D = f(t)</m>. The notation <m>f(t)</m> is read as, <q><m>f</m> of <m>t</m></q>.</p>
        <p>Remember <m>t</m> is a value.  The function uses <m>t</m> to create the value <m>D</m>.</p>
        <p>Also, don't confuse the notation with multiplication!  <m>f(t)</m> does <alert>not</alert> mean <m>f</m> times <m>t</m>.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$tarzan">
                        <set>
                            <member>\text{Tarzan times the jungle}</member>
                            <member>\text{Tarzan jungle}</member>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{Tarzan of the jungle}</member>
                            <member>\text{jungle after Tarzan}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$helen">
                        <set>
                            <member>\text{Helen loves Troy}</member>
                            <member>\text{Helen multiplied by Troy}</member>
                            <member>\text{Helen Troy}</member>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{Helen of Troy}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$f">
                        <set>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{f of x}</member>
                            <member>\text{f times x}</member>
                            <member>\text{f parentheses x}</member>
                            <member>\text{f x}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $tarzan = PopUp(["?","Tarzan times the jungle","Tarzan jungle","Tarzan of the jungle","Jungle after Tarzan"],"Tarzan of the jungle");
                        $helen = PopUp(["?","Helen loves Troy","Helen multiplied by Troy","Helen next to Troy","Helen of Troy"],"Helen of Troy");
                        $f = PopUp(["?","f of x","f times x","f parentheses x","f x"],"f of x");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>How would you say the function notation in each statement below?<ol>
                        <li>
                            <p>Tarzan(the jungle) <var name="$tarzan" form="popup" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Helen(Troy) <var name="$helen" form="popup" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p><m>f(x)</m> <var name="$f" form="popup" /></p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>Function notation like <m>f(t)</m> or <m>f(x)</m> or <m>f(\text{anything})</m> implies there is some kind of relation, some kind of rule, that takes a piece of information and returns a response or result. The format of function notation works on the basic principle of input and output and we often use the notation when we refer to things we don't yet know.</p>

        <p>For instance, if you work as a health assistant, you probably earn some hourly salary and you probably work some number of hours each week.  I have no idea how many hours a week you work and no idea how much you earn.  But I do know your weekly salary is related to the number of hours you work. In fact, your weekly salary is a function of the number of hours you work.</p>
        <p>If <m>t</m> is the number of hours you work and <m>S</m> is your weekly salary, I can use function notation to say, <m>S = f(t)</m> where <m>f(t)</m> is the function, the instructions, that calculates your weekly salary.  If you work <m>12</m> hours, then <m>t = 12</m> so <m>f(12)</m> is your weekly salary for working <m>12</m> hours.</p>
        <p>Notice I still don't know what the salary actually is, but I can use function notation to talk about it.  <m>f(12)</m> literally means, <q>whatever you earn when you work <m>12</m> hours.</q></p>

        <p>In our train example we chose some input, a time, and the function gives an output of distance.  The notation tells the reader what the input is by showing it in the parentheses.<me>f(\text{input}) = \mathit{output}</me> The function notation <m>f(0)</m> is telling us the input is <m>0</m>.  That means, <q><m>0</m> hours after 8 <init>a.m.</init></q> In other words it's 8 a.m.</p>

        <p>On the other hand, <m>f(0)</m> represents an output. It is <q>the train's distance from downtown <m>0</m> hours after 8 a.m.</q>. But we don't know what that distance actually is yet. <m>f(0)</m> in this case means, <q>What ever the distance is at t = 0</q>.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the input and output create an <term>ordered pair</term><index><main>ordered pair</main></index> <m>(0, f(0))</m>.  On a graph the ordered pair is a <term>point</term><index><main>point</main></index>.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$distance">
                        <static>10</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$units">
                        <set>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{miles}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours}</member>
                             <member>\text{miles per hour}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours per mile}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$start">
                        <static>8</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$ampm">
                        <set>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{a.m.}</member>
                             <member>\text{p.m.}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$meanings">
                        <set>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{the initial position of the train}</member>
                             <member>\text{the final position of the train}</member>
                             <member>\text{the distance is zero}</member>
                             <member>\text{the distance times zero}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$f2">
                        <static>f(2)</static>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $distance = Real(10);
                        $units = PopUp(["?", "miles", "hours", "miles per hour", "hours per mile"], "miles");
                        $start = 8;
                        $ampm = PopUp(["?", "a.m.", "p.m."], "a.m.");
                        $meanings = PopUp(["?", "the initial position of the train", "the final position of the train", "the distance is zero", "the distance times zero"], 1);
                        parserFunction("f(x)"=>"(sin(x)+2)/pi");
                        Context()->flags->set(reduceConstantFunctions=>0);
                        Context()->flags->set(formatStudentAnswer=>"parsed");
                        $f2=Formula("f(2)");
                        $evf2=$f2->cmp()->withPostFilter(AnswerHints(Compute("30") => "That's the actual value, but respond by using function notation."));
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>The graph below is a function that illustrates a train's distance from downtown, in miles,  as a function of time in hours after 8 a.m.  When using a graph the best you can do is estimate. Since <m>f(0)</m> represents a distance at 8 <init>a.m.</init>, we can use the graph to find what the distance is.</p>

                    <p>Move the point onto <m>(0,f(0))</m>.</p>

                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/P6uUYQqH/width/402/height/499/border/888888/rc/false/ai/false/sdz/false/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/true/ld/false/sri/false/at/auto" width="402px" height="499px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                    <p><m>f(0)\approx</m> <var name="$distance" width="5" /> <var name="$units" form="popup" /></p>

                    <p>What time is the function notation <m>f(0)</m> referring to?</p>
                    <p><var name="$start" width="5" />:00 <var name="$ampm" form="popup" /></p>

                    <p>The notation <m>f(0)</m> is read as <q><m>f</m> of zero.</q> What do you think <m>f(0)</m> means in the context of the train story?</p>
                    <p><var name="$meanings" form="popup" /></p>

                    <p>How would you represent the statement, <q>train's distance at 10 a.m.</q> using function notation?</p>
                    <p><var name="$f2" width="10" evaluator="$evf2"/></p>

                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>Here is another example to further explore the use function notation.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$squarefeet">
                        <static>900</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$sqft">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{square inches}</member>
                             <member>\text{dollars}</member>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{square feet}</member>
                             <member>\text{cubic yards}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$HouseValue">
                        <static>209700</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$units">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{cents}</member>
                             <member>\text{turtles}</member>
                             <member>\text{yen}</member>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{dollars}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$meaning">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{900 houses have 209,700 dollars}</member>
                             <member>\text{A 900 dollar house is 209,700 sq. feet}</member>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{A 900 sq. ft. house has a value of 209,700 dollars}</member>
                             <member>\text{Multiply the sq. ft. by 900 to get the value of 209,700 dollars}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $squarefeet= Real(900);
                        $sqft = PopUp(["?", "square inches", "dollars", "square feet", "cubic yards"], "square feet");
                        $HouseValue= Real(209700);
                        $units = PopUp(["?", "cents", "turtles", "yen", "dollars"], "dollars");
                        $meaning = PopUp(["?", "900 houses have 209,700 dollars", "A 900 dollar house is 209,700 sq. feet", "A 900 sq. ft. house has a value of 209,700 dollars", "Multiply the sq. ft. by 900 to get the value of 209,700 dollars"], "A 900 sq. ft. house has a value of 209,700 dollars");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Let <m>V = f(A)</m> be a function in which the input is area of a house measured in square feet and the output is the value of the house in dollars.</p>

                    <p>Consider the equation <m>f(900) = 209{,}700</m>.  The notation gives us information about the house.</p>

                    <p>Given <m>f(900) = 209{,}700</m>, what is the area of the house?</p>
                    <p><var name="$squarefeet" width="5" /> <var name="$sqft" form="popup" /></p>

                    <p>What is the value of the house?</p>
                    <p><var name="$HouseValue" width="5" /> <var name="$units" form="popup" /></p>

                    <p>Interpret the meaning of the equation <m>f(900) = 209{,}700</m> in English.</p>
                    <p><var name="$meaning" form="popup" /></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
    </subsection>
    <subsection>
        <title>How to Determine if a Relation is a Function or Not</title>
        <p>When two or more variables are related to each other, the formula or rule that relates them is called a <term>relation</term>.  There is a relation between age and height, you can make ordered pairs of <m>(\text{age}, \text{height})</m> for different people and plot the points on a graph. You might even find a formula that predicts height based on age (or vice versa?)</p>
        <p>In every relation you have encountered so far in this chapter, each input gives you only one output. Earlier, for the train example we had the function <m>D = f(t)</m>. At any given time, like <m>t = 10</m>, the train can only be in one place, <m>f(10)</m>. It's not possible for the train to be in two or more places at the same time.</p>
        <p>Also notice that each input has its own unique output. Every day, at <m>t = 10</m> the train is always in the same place, <m>f(10) = 30</m> (it's a very dependable train). These two conditions make the relation a function. Postion is a function of time.</p>
        <p>But not all relations are functions. Just because two things are related does not mean one is a function of the other.</p>
        <p>Twice each day the train is <m>30</m> miles away from downtown. Once in the morning at on its way out, then later in the afternoon on the way back into town. If we choose postion as input and time as output we realize that the input <m>D = 30</m> gives us two answers: one time in the morning and another in the afternoon.  Thus time is not a function of position. All we have is a relation.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$situation1">
                        <set>
                            <member>\text{yes}</member>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{no}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$situation2">
                        <set>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{yes}</member>
                            <member>\text{no}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $situation1 = RadioButtons(
                            ["yes","no"],
                            1,
                        );
                        $situation2 = RadioButtons(
                            ["yes","no"],
                             0,
                        );
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Decide if each situation is possible given the function <m>y = f(x)</m> where <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are just generic variables.</p>
                    <p><ol label="a">
                        <li>
                            <p>Is it possible that <m>f(3)=10</m> and <m>f(3) = 17</m>?</p>
                            <p><var name="$situation1" form="buttons" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Is it possible that <m>f(3)=10</m> and <m>f(8) = 10</m>?</p>
                            <p><var name="$situation2" form="buttons" /></p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
        <p>Tables are one way to express inputs and outputs of a relation. In a vertical table the inputs are on the left while the outputs are on the right.  In a horizontal table, the top row is the input and the bottom row is the output.</p>

        <table>
          <caption>Vertical Table</caption>
            <tabular>
                <col right="medium"/>
                <col />
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell><em>Input</em></cell>
                    <cell><em>Output</em></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>input</cell>
                    <cell>output</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>input</cell>
                    <cell>output</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>input</cell>
                    <cell>output</cell>
                </row>
            </tabular>
        </table>

        <table>
          <caption>Horizontal Table</caption>
            <tabular>
                <col right="medium"/>
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell><em>Input</em></cell>
                    <cell>input</cell>
                    <cell>input</cell>
                    <cell>input</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><em>Output</em></cell>
                    <cell>output</cell>
                    <cell>output</cell>
                    <cell>output</cell>
                </row>
            </tabular>
        </table>
        <exercise>
          <title>Determine if the relation in each table is a function or not</title>
          <webwork>
            <setup>
              <var name="$table1">
                <set>
                  <member>\text{This table is a function}</member>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This table is not a function}</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <var name="$table2">
                <set>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This table is a function}</member>
                  <member>\text{This table is not a function}</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <pg-code>
                $table1 = RadioButtons(["Table A is a function","Table A is not a function"],1);
                $table2 = RadioButtons(["Table B is a function","Table B is not a function"],0);
              </pg-code>
            </setup>
            <statement>
                <p><ol label="A">
                    <li>
                        <p>Does this table describe a function?</p>
                        <tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>x</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>y</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>8</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>10</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>-8</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                            </row>
                        </tabular>
                        <p><var name="$table1" form="buttons" /></p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>Does this table describe a function?</p>
                        <tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>x</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>y</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>8</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>10</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>-8</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                            </row>
                        </tabular>
                        <p><var name="$table2" form="buttons" /></p>
                    </li>
                </ol></p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
              <p>Table A is not a function because the input <m>x = 5</m> yields more than one result.</p>
              <p>Table B is a function because each input yields only one result. It does not matter that the results are all the same. This is an example of a <term>constant function</term>.</p>
            </solution>
          </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
          <title>Determine if each equation makes <m>y</m> a function of <m>x</m></title>
          <webwork>
            <setup>
              <var name="$eq1">
                <set>
                  <member>\text{This equation makes }y\text{ a function of }x</member>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This equation does not make }y\text{ a function of }x</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <var name="$eq2">
                <set>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This equation makes }y\text{ a function of }x</member>
                  <member>\text{This equation does not make }y\text{ a function of }x</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <pg-code>
                $eq1 = RadioButtons(["This equation makes y a function of x","This equation does not make y a function of x"],0);
                $eq2 = RadioButtons(["This equation makes y a function of x","This equation does not make y a function of x"],1);
              </pg-code>
            </setup>
            <statement>
                <p><ol label="a">
                    <li>
                        <p>Is <m>y</m> a function of <m>x</m> if, <m>y=x^2</m>?</p>
                        <p><var name="$eq1" form="buttons" /></p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>Is <m>y</m> a function of <m>x</m> if, <m>y^2=x</m>?</p>
                        <p><var name="$eq2" form="buttons" /></p>
                    </li>
                </ol></p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <p>In each case, ask yourself what happens when you choose a value for <m>x</m>?  Do you get one output or do you get more than one output?</p>
                <p><ol label="a">
                    <li>
                        <p>Is <m>y</m> a function of <m>x</m> if, <m>y=x^2</m>?</p>
                        <p>Yes <m>y</m> is a function of <m>x</m> because for any value of <m>x</m> you pick, there is only one possible <m>y</m> as a result.</p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>Is <m>y</m> a function of <m>x</m> if, <m>y^2=x</m>?</p>
                        <p>No <m>y</m> is not function of <m>x</m> because when you solve for <m>y</m> you get the equation <m>y = \pm \sqrt{x}</m></p>
                    </li>
                </ol></p>
            </solution>
          </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>When looking at a graph it's easy to tell if the graph is that of a function or not.  Remember the inputs are found along the horizontal axis while the outputs are found along the vertical axis.  The rule is the same: one input, one unique output.</p>

        <exercise>
          <title>Determine if the graph is a function</title>
          <webwork>
            <setup>
              <var name="$nopass">
                <set>
                  <member>\text{This graph is a function}</member>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This graph is not a function}</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <var name="$pass">
                <set>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This graph is a function}</member>
                  <member>\text{This graph is not a function}</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <pg-code>
                $nopass = RadioButtons(["This graph is a function","This graph is not a function"],1);
                $pass = RadioButtons(["This graph is a function","This graph is not a function"],0);
              </pg-code>
            </setup>
            <statement>
                <p>Drag the input left or right to see the results on each graph. Think about how many outputs each input yields.</p>
                <p><ol label="a">
                    <li>
                        <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/QTfyBkEb/width/413/height/266/border/888888" width="413px" height="266px" style="border:0px;" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                        <p><var name="$nopass" form="buttons" /></p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/Req8ZfCM/width/413/height/290/border/888888" width="413px" height="290px" style="border:0px;" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                        <p><var name="$pass" form="buttons" /></p>
                    </li>
                </ol></p>
            </statement>
            <hint>
                <p>Think about how many outputs each input yields.</p>
            </hint>
          </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>The previous example leads us to a simple test we can use to determine if a graph is a function or not.  It's called the <term>vertical line test</term><index><main>vertical line test</main></index>.</p>

        <p>Given a graph, draw a vertical line through any place on the graph. If the vertical line crosses the graph at most one time (no matter where you draw the line), then the graph is a funciton. If the vertical line crosses the graph anywhere at more than one point, then the graph is not a function.</p>

        <exercise xml:id="exercise-vertical-line-test">
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$none">
                        <static>1</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$no">
                      <set>
                        <member>\text{Passes Vertical Line Test}</member>
                        <member correct="yes">\text{Does not pass Vertical Line Test}</member>
                      </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$yes">
                      <set>
                        <member>\text{Passes Vertical Line Test}</member>
                        <member correct="yes">\text{Does not pass Vertical Line Test}</member>
                      </set>
                    </var>

                    <pg-code>
                        $none = Real(1);
                        $no = RadioButtons(["Passes Vertical Line Test","Does not pass Vertical Line Test"],1);
                        $yes = RadioButtons(["Passes Vertical Line Test","Does not pass Vertical Line Test"],0);
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <p>Drag the input to change the postion of the vertical line.</p>
                    <p>Does the line intersect the graph more than once?  If so, it does not pass the vertical line test and the graph is not a function.</p>
                    <p><ol label="a">
                        <li>
                            <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/tqS4kTMd/width/413/height/331/border/888888" width="413px" height="331px" style="border:0px;" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                            <p><var name="$no" form="buttons" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/zepNEn3W/width/413/height/331/border/888888" width="413px" height="331px" style="border:0px;" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                            <p><var name="$yes" form="buttons" /></p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Evaluate</title>
        <p>It's one thing to talk about <q>The train's distance from downtown <m>2</m> hours after 8 a.m.</q> and a completely different thing to say what that distance actually is.</p>
        <p><term>Evaluate</term><index><main>Evaluate</main></index> means to <em>find the value of the output given an input value.</em>  Therefore, evaluate <m>f(2)</m>, in our train example means <q>Find the value of the train's distance from downtown <m>2</m> hours after 8 a.m.</q></p>
        <p>To <term>evaluate</term> <m>f(2)</m> we can use a graph, a table or a formula if they are avaible.</p>
        <p>The important thing is we need some time input value to determine the output value for the train's distance from downtown. Also, for each input the function yields only one result and each individual input always gives the same single result.</p>
        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$dist">
                        <static>40</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$miles">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{feet}</member>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{miles}</member>
                             <member>\text{light years}</member>
                             <member>\text{meters}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $dist= Real(40);
                        $miles = PopUp(["?", "feet", "miles", "light years", "meters"], "miles");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <table>
                        <tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>t</m> (hours after 8 a.m.)</cell>
                                <cell><m>D = f(t)</m> (miles from downtown)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>10</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>0.5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>12</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>1.5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>20</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>2.5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>40</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>3.0</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>46</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>3.5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>47</m></cell>
                            </row>
                        </tabular>
                    </table>
                    <p>Remember in a vertical table the inputs are found in the left column (independent variable) while outputs are found in the right column (dependent variable)</p>
                    <p>Use the table to evaluate <m>f(2.5)</m></p>
                    <p><m>f(2.5)= </m><var name="$dist" width="5" /> <var name="$miles" form="popup" /></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>In general when the inputs and outputs are nothing in particular, we use <m>x</m> as input and <m>y</m> as output so that <m>y = f(x)</m>.  We use <q><m>x</m></q> as symbol to hold a spot for the actual input value while <q><m>y</m></q> is a spot holder for whatever the output value will be.  The <m>x</m> basically says, <q>When you get the input, put it here</q> in all the places where the <m>x</m> is found.</p>

        <p>Consider the function <m>f(x) = 50x + 10</m>.  The function has no context (no story) so we won't bother using units for either <m>x</m> or <m>y</m>.</p>

        <p>If <m>x = 1</m> then we can evaluate <m>f(1)</m>  by replacing the <q><m>x</m></q> in the formula with a <m>1</m>.  Literally, <m>f(1)</m> means, <q>Whatever you get when you put <m>1</m> into the formula</q>.</p>
        <p>Similarly, if you change the input to <m>x = 2</m> then you can evaluate the function <m>f(2)</m>, where <m>f(2)</m> represents, <q>Whatever you get when you put <m>2</m> into the formula</q>.</p>
        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$in1">
                        <static>1</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$in2">
                        <static>2</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$output1">
                        <static>60</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$output2">
                        <static>110</static>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $in1 = Real(1);
                        $in2 = Real(2);
                        $output1 = Real(60);
                        $output2 = Real(110);
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Let <m>f(x) = 50x + 10</m>.  Evaluate the expressions below:</p>
                    <p><ol label="a">
                        <li>
                            <p>What do you get when you put <m>1</m> into the formula?</p>
                            <p><m>f(1) = 50 \big(</m><var name="$in1" width="2" /><m>\big)+ 10</m></p>
                            <p><m>f(1) = </m> <var name="$output1" width="5" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>What do you get when you put <m>2</m> into the formula?</p>
                            <p><m>f(2) = 50\big(</m><var name="$in2" width="2" /><m>\big)+ 10</m></p>
                            <p><m>f(2) = </m> <var name="$output2" width="5" /></p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$output1">
                        <static>0</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$output2">
                        <static>0</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$output3">
                        <static>0</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$output4">
                        <static>-1.54</static>
                    </var>

                    <pg-code>
                        $output1 = Real(0);
                        $output2 = Real(0);
                        $output3 = Real(0);
                        $output4 = Real(-1.54);
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <p>The graph the the function <m>f(x)</m> is shown below.</p>
                    <p>To evaluate the function, drag the crosshair (green) on the horizontal axis to the desired input value. Then measure the height of the graph from the vertical axis (red) to find the output value.</p>

                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/AKbM4T7B/width/431/height/415/border/888888/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/false/ai/false/asb/false/sri/false/rc/false/ld/false/sdz/false/ctl/false" width="431px" height="415px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                    <p><ol label="a">
                        <li>
                            <p>Evaluate <m>f(-4)</m></p>
                            <p><m>f(-4) = </m> <var name="$output1" width="5" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Evaluate <m>f(-1)</m></p>
                            <p><m>f(-1) = </m> <var name="$output2" width="5" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Evaluate <m>f(0)</m></p>
                            <p><m>f(0) = </m> <var name="$output4" width="5" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Evaluate <m>f(2)</m></p>
                            <p><m>f(2) = </m> <var name="$output3" width="5" /></p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                    <p>Notice how each input yields only one result (there is only one answer for each input) but some inputs have the same output value.  It's no coincidence the graph passes the vertical line test!</p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>The Secret to Evaluating Anything (The <q>Blank</q> Method)</title>

        <p>Function notation is a way to tell the reader information about the input and how to use it to generate an output. Again, the way it works is <m>f(\text{input})=\text{output}</m>. Whatever is in the parenthesis is the input.</p>

        <p>The input can be a simple number like <m>2</m> or <m>-4</m> or the input can be a complicated expression like <m>x^2 - x</m>.</p>

        <p>Your success in this course is almost entirely dependent on your understanding of this simple concept: <em>The <q>blank</q> method.</em></p>

        <p>When you see a formula like <m>f(x) = x^2 - x</m>. It means this:<me>f(\text{blank}) = (\text{blank})^2 - (\text{blank})</me></p>

        <p>At least that's the way formulas really work.</p>

        <p>Using this function as an example, <m>f(5)</m> means <q>The formula with a <m>5</m> in it</q>. Literally it means place number <m>5</m> in all the blanks.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$five">
                        <static>5</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$out">
                        <static>20</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$M">
                        <static>M</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$Mexp">
                        <static>M^2-M</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$Q">
                        <static>Q</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$Qexp">
                        <static>Q^2-Q</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$P">
                        <static>x-12</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$expression">
                        <static>(x-12)^2-(x-12)</static>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $five = Real(5);
                        $out = Real(20);
                        Context()->variables->are(M=>'Real', Q=>'Real', x=>'Real');
                        $M=Compute("M");
                        $Q=Compute("Q");
                        $P=Compute("x-12");
                        $Mexp=Compute("M**2-M");
                        $Qexp=Compute("Q**2-Q");
                        $expression=Compute("(x-12)**2-(x-12)");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Use the function <m>f(x) = x^2 - x</m> to evaluate <m>f(5)</m>.</p>
                    <p>If you need to write an exponent like <m>x^{2}</m> use your keyboard and type <m>x \text{^} 2</m> the symbol ^ is above the number <m>6</m> on your keyboard.</p>
                    <p><ol label="a">
                        <li>
                            <p>Replace all the <m>x</m>'s in the formula with parentheses to create blank spaces. As in</p>
                            <p><m>f(\text{blank}) = (\text{blank})^2 - (\text{blank})</m>.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Identify the intput.</p>
                            <p>In this case the given input is <var name="$five" width="2" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Place the input into all the blank spaces.</p>
                            <p><m>f(5) = \big(</m> <var name="$five" width="2" /><m>\big)^2 - \big(</m> <var name="$five" width="2" /><m>\big)</m></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                           <p>Evaluate the function.</p>
                            <p><m>f(5) = </m><var name="$out" width="2" /></p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                    <p>Using the same method, evaluate each of the following expressions (do not simplify):</p>
                    <p>Keep in mind in Math the variable <m>M</m> is completely different thant <m>m</m>. Be careful to distinguish between lower case and capital variables!</p>
                    <p><ol label="a">
                        <li>
                            <p><m>f(M) = \big(</m> <var name="$M" width="2" /><m>\big)^2 - \big(</m> <var name="$M" width="2" /><m>\big)</m></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p><m>f(M) = </m> <var name="$Mexp" width="5" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p><m>f(Q) = \big(</m> <var name="$Q" width="2" /><m>\big)^2 - \big(</m> <var name="$Q" width="2" /><m>\big)</m></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p><m>f(Q) = </m> <var name="$Qexp" width="5" /></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p><m>f(x-12) = \big(</m> <var name="$P" width="2" /><m>\big)^2 - \big(</m> <var name="$P" width="2" /><m>\big)</m></p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p><m>f(x-12) = </m> <var name="$expression" width="20" /></p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>The beauty of this is it does <em>not</em> matter what you put into the formula (as long as the formula can handle it which we will get into later), the formula does the same thing every time.</p>

        <p>You can put <m>5</m> into the formula or you can put something complicated into the formula like <m>\frac{x^2}{x^2 + 1}</m> which would look like this<me>f\mathopen{}\left(\frac{x^2}{x^2 + 1}\right)\mathclose{} = \mathopen{}\left(\frac{x^2}{x^2 + 1}\right)^2\mathclose{} - \mathopen{}\left(\frac{x^2}{x^2 + 1}\right)\mathclose{}</me></p>

        <p>Simplifying this expression is another matter.</p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Solve</title>

        <p>What if the output, the result, is already known and we want to know all the inputs that give us this result?  This is called <term>solve</term><index><main>solve</main></index>.</p>
        <p>If you live in Oregon in the winter, you might ask, <q>What time will the temperature outside be <m>37</m> degrees fahrenheit?</q> Typically there might be two answers to this question, one time in the morning and another time in the afternoon.</p>
        <p>You could answer the question with actual times if you had a time <init>vs.</init> temperature graph or a formula or a table of times and temperatures.</p>
        <p>Solve means to work backwards from a known or given output value and determine all the inputs, if any, that give us the desired output.</p>
        <p>Suppose we want the output of a function to be <m>y =0</m>. Therefore, we must find all the input values of <m>x</m> that gives us that result. There may not be any, but there could be one, several or even infinite possible inputs that gives <m>y = 0</m> as the output.</p>
        <exercise>
          <webwork>
              <title>Solving Graphically</title>
              <setup>
                  <var name="$numZeros">
                      <static>3</static>
                  </var>
                  <var name="$zeros">
                      <static>-4,-1,2</static>
                  </var>
                  <var name="$numSolutions1">
                      <static>2</static>
                  </var>
                  <var name="$solutions">
                      <static>-2.7,2.46</static>
                  </var>
                  <var name="$numSolutions2">
                      <static>1</static>
                  </var>
                  <var name="$solutions2">
                      <static>2.64</static>
                  </var>
                  <var name="$maxNumSolutions">
                      <static>3</static>
                  </var>
                   <var name="$minNumSolutions">
                      <static>1</static>
                  </var>


                  <pg-code>
                      $numZeros = 3;
                      $zeros = List(-4,-1,2);
                      $numSolutions1 = 2;
                      $solutions = List(-2.7,2.46);
                      $numSolutions2 = 1;
                      $solutions2 = List(2.64);
                      $maxNumSolutions = 3;
                      $minNumSolutions = 1;

                  </pg-code>
              </setup>

              <stage>
                  <statement>
                      <p>On a graph the output is the height of the graph.</p>
                      <p>Therefore,<q>Solve <m>f(x) = 0</m></q> on a graph means, <q>Find all the input values on the <m>x</m>-axis where the graph reaches a height of <m>y = 0</m></q></p>
                      <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/CPtFHaPP/width/431/height/355/border/888888/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/false/ai/false/asb/false/sri/false/rc/false/ld/false/sdz/false/ctl/false" width="431px" height="355px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                      <p>Drag the point on the vertical axis (black cross symbol) to the desired output value.  The graph will show all the places (red points) where the function reaches the chosen output value.</p>
                      <p>The solutions (if any) are shown on the horizontal axis in green.</p>

                      <p>To solve the equation <m>f(x) = 0</m> graphically, move the height of the horizontal line to <m>y = 0</m></p>

                      <p>The horizontal line intersects with <m>f(x)</m> <var name="$numZeros" width="5" /> times.</p>

                      <p>The solutions to <m>f(x) = 0</m> are <m>x=</m><var name="$zeros" width="15" />. (Use commas.)</p>

                      <p>Notice that all the <m>y</m>-values are <m>0</m>, but the <m>x</m>-values are different.  The <m>x</m>-values are the <em>solutions to the equation <m>f(x) = 0</m></em>.</p>
                  </statement>
              </stage>

              <stage>
                <statement>
                  <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/CPtFHaPP/width/431/height/355/border/888888/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/false/ai/false/asb/false/sri/false/rc/false/ld/false/sdz/false/ctl/false" width="431px" height="355px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                  <p>Move the horizontal line to <m>y = 2</m>. Use this line to solve the equation <m>f(x) = 2</m></p>

                  <p>How many solutions does the equation have? If there are none, type <q>none</q>.</p>
                  <p>The equation has <var name="$numSolutions1" width="5" /> solution(s).</p>

                  <p>Use the <m>x</m>-coordinates of the points on the horizontal axis to determine all the solutions to the equation.</p>
                  <p>The solution(s) to <m>f(x) = 2</m> is/are: <m>x=</m><var name="$solutions" width="15" />. (Use commas to separate multiple answers if necessary.)</p>
                </statement>
              </stage>

              <stage>
                <statement>
                  <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/CPtFHaPP/width/431/height/355/border/888888/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/false/ai/false/asb/false/sri/false/rc/false/ld/false/sdz/false/ctl/false" width="431px" height="355px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                  <p>Adjust the height of the horizontal line to solve <m>f(x) = 3</m></p>
                  <p>How many solutions does this equation have?</p>
                  <p>There is/are <var name="$numSolutions2" width="5" /> solution(s).</p>

                  <p>The solution(s) to <m>f(x) = 3</m> is/are: <m>x=</m><var name="$solutions2" width="15" />. (Use commas to separate multiple answers if necessary.)</p>
                </statement>
              </stage>

              <stage>
                <statement>
                  <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/CPtFHaPP/width/431/height/355/border/888888/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/false/ai/false/asb/false/sri/false/rc/false/ld/false/sdz/false/ctl/false" width="431px" height="355px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                  <p>Suppose the value of <m>y</m> could be anything.  Using the graph and the adjustable horizontal line, What is the maximum number of possible solutions for the equation <m>f(x) = y</m>?</p>

                  <p>The maximum number of solutions is <var name="$maxNumSolutions" width="5" /> </p>

                  <p>What is the minimum number of possible solutions for the equation?</p>

                  <p>The minimum number of solutions is <var name="$minNumSolutions" width="5" /> </p>
                </statement>
              </stage>
          </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>In English we could ask the question for the example in the previous exercise,</p>

        <blockquote>
            <p>What input makes the output equal to <m>0</m>?</p>
        </blockquote>

        <p>There would be three answers:<me>x = - 4 , -1\text{ or }2</me></p>

        <p>All of these values of <m>x</m> give us the same result of <m>y = 0</m>.</p>

        <p>In math we could ask the same question, but it comes out as a statement.</p>

        <blockquote>
            <p>Solve <m>f(x) = 0</m></p>
        </blockquote>

        <p>In other words, <q>Find the input that gives you a particular result</q>.  In our case the result we want is an output value of <m>0</m>. There are still three answers to the question and each answer is called a <q>solution</q>.</p>

        <p>The statement:</p>

        <blockquote>
            <p>Solve <m>f(x) = 0</m></p>
        </blockquote>

        <p>has three solutions:  <me>x = -4, -1 \text{ or }2</me></p>

        <p>If we look at functions graphically, the math sentence</p>

        <blockquote>
          <p>Solve the equation <m>f(x) = K</m></p>
        </blockquote>

        <p>where <m>K</m> is some number, means to <q>find all the <m>x</m>-values where the graph of the function reaches a height of <m>K</m> units high.</q> this equation may have one, several, or infinite or even no solutions.</p>
        <p>Even equations where a formula equals another formula can be solved graphically. Consider <me>2^x + 0.025 = 0.55x - 0.3</me>To solve graphically, make a graph on your graphing calculator, then find the <m>x</m> values where the graphs have the same output (height). In other words, find where the graphs intersect.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$answer1">
                        <static>1.5</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$answer2">
                        <static>0</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$answer3">
                        <static>1</static>
                    </var>

                    <pg-code>
                        $b = 0.55/ln(2) - 0.55*ln(0.5/ln(2)) / ln(2);
                        $answer1 = Real(1.5);
                        $evaluator1 = $answer1->cmp(checker => sub {
                           my ($correct,$student,$ansHash) = @_;
                           return (($student &gt; $b)?1:0);
                         });
                        $answer2 = Real(0);
                        $evaluator2 = $answer2->cmp(checker => sub {
                           my ($correct,$student,$ansHash) = @_;
                           return (($student &lt; $b)?1:0);
                         });
                         $answer3 = Real(1);
                        $evaluator3 = $answer3->cmp(checker => sub {
                           my ($correct,$student,$ansHash) = @_;
                           return (($student = $b)?1:0);
                         });
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <p>The graphs of two functions are shown, one is linear <m>y = 0.55x - 0.3</m> and the other <m>f(x)=2^x + 0.025</m> is called <em>exponential</em>. Solving the equation <me>2^x + 0.025 = 0.55x -0.3</me> would not be possible using our current algebra techniques. But in English, solving the equation means to find where the functions intersect. That we can do quite easily using graphs.</p>

                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/rZySMTyJ/width/413/height/331/border/888888" width="413px" height="331px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                    <p><ol label="a">
                        <li>
                            <p>Find a value for <m>b</m> such that the equation<me>2^x + 0.025 = 0.55x + b</me>has two solutions.</p>
                            <p>If <m>b = </m><var name="$answer1" evaluator="$evaluator1" width="3" /> then the equation would have two solutions.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Find a value for <m>b</m> such that the equation<me>2^x + 0.025= 0.55x + b</me>has no solutions.</p>
                            <p>If <m>b = </m><var name="$answer2" evaluator="$evaluator2" width="3" /> then the equation would have no solutions.</p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>Find a value for <m>b</m> such that the equation<me>2^x + 0.025= 0.55x + b</me>has only one solution.</p>
                            <p>If <m>b = </m><var name="$answer3" evaluator="$evaluator3" width="3" /> then the equation would have no solutions.</p>
                        </li>
                    </ol></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
        <p>Often equations are too difficult or even impossible to solve using algebra.  But if you can graph the equations on a graphing calculator or on the web, you can solve graphically to get at least approximate solutions.</p>
    </subsection>
</section>
