<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->

<section xml:id="activity-functions-function-notation" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Function Notation (Input, Output)</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>In this activity we develop an understanding of function notation by comparing statements we already understand in English to equivalent statements written in <q>math</q> language.   We interpret our statements about functions using graphs, tables and formulas.</p>

    <todo>
    <p>There are <m>34</m> questions in this activity.  All questions need to be answered correctly in order for the activity to be complete.  Each question is numbered and is written in bold.  A correct answer will show <q>correct</q> while an incorrect answer will show <q>Try again</q>.</p>
    <p>At the end of the activity you will see how many questions you answered correctly.</p>
    </todo>
        <p>After completing this lesson you will be able to:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>Interpret the meaning of function notation.</p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Use function notation to describe an event.</p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Evaluate a function.</p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p>The prerequisites for this lesson are knowing how to read a graph or a table of values and how to use a formula to make a calculation.</p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <title>Math as a Language</title>
        <p>We begin this activity by realizing math is just another language and everything you say or describe in English, you can say or describe in Math. Math is a language specifically to communicate measurements, or values and relationships.</p>
        <p>In this next exercise we learn to communicate the position of a train as time passes and develop the notation to express where the train is at different times.</p>
        
        <exercise>
            <webwork seed="1">
                <setup>
                    <var name="$time">
                        <static>2</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$position">
                        <static>30</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$units" category="set">
                        <set>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{miles}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours}</member>
                             <member>\text{miles per hour}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours per mile}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $time = Real(random(2,7,1));
                        if($envir{problemSeed}==1){$time=2;};
                        $position = Real(40*exp(2.6*($time-2))/(1+exp(2.6*($time-2)))+10);
                        $units = PopUp(["?", "miles", "hours", "miles per hour", "hours per mile"], "miles");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Consider the graph below.</p>

                    <p>The dot on the graph represents the position of a train at a particular time. The blue crosshairs represent the time.</p>

                    <p>Adjust the time by sliding crosshairs left and right.  Notice that the train's distance, in miles, from downtown depends on the time, in hours, after 8 a.m.</p>

                    <p>Without knowing anything about function notation, you can still use a language you already know, English, to describe information about the train.</p>

                    <p>For instance:
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                <p>The train can only be in one place at any particular time.</p>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <p>As time passes the train gets farther from downtown.</p>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <p>The speed of the train changes during its trip.</p>
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>


                    <p>There are also some aspects of the graph itself that you can easily describe in English:
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                <p>The graph rises as we read it from left to right.</p>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <p>Sometimes the graph is curved upwards.</p>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <p>Sometimes the graph curves downwards.</p>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <p>Some parts of the graph are steeper than others.</p>
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>

                    <p>In this lesson we learn to describe situations in math language using function notation.  Later the notation itself will allow us to use math in making calculations.</p>

                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/D4s2v4ft/width/450/height/459/border/888888/rc/false/ai/false/sdz/false/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/true/ld/false/sri/false/at/auto" width="450px" height="459px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                    <p>How far from downtown is the train <m><var name="$time" /></m> hours after 8 a.m.?</p>

                    <p><var name="$position" width="5" /> <var name="$units" form="popup" /></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>In English you can communicate information about time and position in a simple sentence like</p>

        <blockquote>English:  <q>2 hours after 8 <init>a.m.</init> the train is 30 miles from downtown</q>.</blockquote>

        <p>Here is what that same sentence looks like in Spanish.</p>

        <blockquote>Spanish:  <q>2 horas despues de las 8 del la mañana el tren esta 30 millas lejos del centro</q>.</blockquote>

        <p>Here is what that same sentence could look like in <q>math</q>.</p>

        <blockquote>Math:  <m>f(2) = 30</m></blockquote>

        <p>Let's piece apart the English sentence so you can see the structure as it compares to math. In Enlgish we tell the reader what we are talking about. This is the subject, <q>The position of the train 2 hours after 8 <int>a.m.</int></q> and in math we can simply say, <m>f(2)</m>.</p>
        <p>Now the reader is wondering, so what about this train's position?  Is it more than something, less than something, is growing, shrinking, what? In our example we just want to say what the distance is. In math <q>is</q> means <q>equals</q> but we use the symbol, <m>=</m>.</p>
        <p>Finally we want to tell the reader the punch line.  We want to tell them that the distance is <m>30</m> miles from downtown at the specified time. Hence, <m>f(2) = 30</m> is the entire senctence.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection>
        <title>The Grammar of Functioin Notation</title>
        <p>The math <q>sentence</q> above is actually an equation and it uses <term>function notation</term> to express the information about the train. Of course, the equation is meaningless unless the reader knows how the notation is defined.  If you know Spanish or <q>math</q> you can <em>interpret</em> the meaning of something you read in those languages into English.  There will be much interpretation in this class.</p>

        <p>In math we use variables and symbols to replace entire words or even entire sentences. For instance, instead of <q>Train's distance in miles from downtown</q> we can use the variable <m>D</m>. Instead of the <q>number of hours after 8 <init>a.m.</init></q>, we can use the variable <m>t</m>.</p>

        <p>We call the letters <m>D</m> and <m>t</m> variables because they represent values that can change.  Typically we use variables that have something to do with the context of the problem, but sometimes we generalize an expression or equation with <m>x</m>'s and <m>y</m>'s when we have nothing specific in mind.</p>

        <p>If the variables represent actual things or events we must define the varialbles to include the units we used to measure the event.</p>

        <blockquote>If <m>D</m> is distance you must define the units in which the distance is measured: miles, inches, centimeters, light years<ellipsis />what?</blockquote>

        <blockquote>If <m>t</m> is time, will it be measured with units of seconds, hours<ellipsis />years?</blockquote>

        <p>Since the position of the train depends on the amount of time that has passed, we say <q>the distance depends on time</q>.  In fact, the distance of the train from downtown is a <term>function of time</term>.</p>

        <p>Function notation allows us to communicate that distance is a function of time by simply writing <m>D = f(t)</m> [say, <q><m>D</m> equals <m>f</m> of <m>t</m></q>].  Don't confuse the notation with multiplication!  <m>f(t)</m> does <alert>not</alert> mean <m>f</m> times <m>t</m>.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$tarzan">
                        <set>
                            <member>\text{Tarzan times the jungle}</member>
                            <member>\text{Tarzan jungle}</member>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{Tarzan of the jungle}</member>
                            <member>\text{jungle after Tarzan}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$helen">
                        <set>
                            <member>\text{Helen loves Troy}</member>
                            <member>\text{Helen multiplied by Troy}</member>
                            <member>\text{Helen Troy}</member>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{Helen of Troy}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$f">
                        <set>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{f of x}</member>
                            <member>\text{f times x}</member>
                            <member>\text{f parentheses x}</member>
                            <member>\text{f x}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $tarzan = PopUp(["?","Tarzan times the jungle","Tarzan jungle","Tarzan of the jungle","Jungle after Tarzan"],"Tarzan of the jungle");
                        $helen = PopUp(["?","Helen loves Troy","Helen multiplied by Troy","Helen next to Troy","Helen of Troy"],"Helen of Troy");
                        $f = PopUp(["?","f of x","f times x","f parentheses x","f x"],"f of x");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>How would you say the function notation in each statement below?</p>
                        <ol>
                            <li>
                                <p>Tarzan(the jungle) <var name="$tarzan" form="popup" /></p>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <p>Helen(Troy) <var name="$helen" form="popup" /></p>
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <p><m>f(x)</m> <var name="$f" form="popup" /></p>
                            </li>
                        </ol>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>The format of function notation works on the basic principle of input and output.</p>

        <p>Choose some input, like a time, and the function gives an output like a distance.  The notation tells the reader what the input is by showing it in the parentheses.<me>f(\text{input}) = \mathit{output}</me> In the train problem, the function notation <m>f(0)</m> is telling us the input is <m>0</m>.  The value <m>0</m> in the parentheses means, <q>0 hours after 8 <init>a.m.</init></q> In other words it's 8 <init>a.m.</init></p>


        <p><m>f(0)</m> is an output.  It represents <q>the train's distance from downtown, <m>0</m> hours after 8 a.m.</q> Together, the input and output create an <term>ordered pair</term> <m>(0, f(0))</m>.  On a graph the ordered pair is a <term>point</term>.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$distance">
                        <static>10</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$units" category="set">
                        <set>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{miles}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours}</member>
                             <member>\text{miles per hour}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours per mile}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $distance = Real(10);
                        $units = PopUp(["?", "miles", "hours", "miles per hour", "hours per mile"], "miles");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>The graph below is a function that illustrates a train's distance from downtown, in miles,  as a function of time in hours after 8 a.m.  When using a graph the best you can do is estimate. Since <m>f(0)</m> represents a distance at 8 <init>a.m.</init>, we can use the graph to find what the distance is.</p>

                    <todo>It would be nice to ask the student to enter more points in function notation form.  If a point is place correctly</todo>

                    <p>Move the point onto <m>(0,f(0))</m>.</p>

                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/P6uUYQqH/width/402/height/499/border/888888/rc/false/ai/false/sdz/false/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/true/ld/false/sri/false/at/auto" width="402px" height="499px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                    <p><m>f(0)\approx</m> <var name="$distance" width="5" /> <var name="$units" form="popup" /></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
            <todo>The questions 6,7,8 from Maple activity act01_function.mw need to be inserted here.  Need to know how to write a question that accepts math text as an input.</todo>
        </exercise>

        <p>Here is another example to further explore the use function notation.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$squarefeet">
                        <static>900</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$sqft" category="set">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{square inches}</member>
                             <member>\text{dollars}</member>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{square feet}</member>
                             <member>\text{cubic yards}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$HouseValue">
                        <static>209700</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$units" category="set">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{cents}</member>
                             <member>\text{turtles}</member>
                             <member>\text{yen}</member>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{dollars}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$meaning" category="set">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{900 houses have 209,700 dollars}</member>
                             <member>\text{A 900 dollar house is 209,700 sq. feet}</member>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{A 900 sq. ft. house has a value of 209,700 dollars}</member>
                             <member>\text{Multiply the sq. ft. by 900 to get the value of 209,700 dollars}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $squarefeet= Real(900);
                        $sqft = PopUp(["?", "square inches", "dollars", "square feet", "cubic yards"], "square feet");
                        $HouseValue= Real(209700);
                        $units = PopUp(["?", "cents", "turtles", "yen", "dollars"], "dollars");
                        $meaning = PopUp(["?", "900 houses have 209,700 dollars", "A 900 dollar house is 209,700 sq. feet", "A 900 sq. ft. house has a value of 209,700 dollars", "Multiply the sq. ft. by 900 to get the value of 209,700 dollars"], "A 900 sq. ft. house has a value of 209,700 dollars");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Let <m>V = f(A)</m> be a function in which the input is area of a house measured in square feet and the output is the value of the house in dollars.</p>
                    <p>Consider the equation <m>f(900) = 209{,}700</m>.  The notation gives us information about the house.</p>
                    <p>Given <m>f(900) = 209{,}700</m>, what is the area of the house?</p>
                    <p><var name="$squarefeet" width="5" /> <var name="$sqft" form="popup" /></p>
                    <p>What is the value of the house?</p>
                    <p><var name="$HouseValue" width="5" /> <var name="$units" form="popup" /></p>
                    <p>Interpret the meaning of the equation <m>f(900) = 209{,}700</m> in English.</p>
                    <p><var name="$meaning" form="popup" /></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
        <title>Evaluate vs Solve</title>
        <p>Its one thing to talk about, <q>The train's distance from downtown 2 hours after 8 a.m.</q> and a completely different thing to say what that distance actually is.</p>

        <p>In our train story <m>f(2)</m> represents the train's distance 2 hours after 8 a.m. To find the value (number) for the distance we must <term>evaluate</term> the funtion. Earlier we used a graph, but can use a table or a formula if there is one avaible. The important thing is we need an input of time to determine the output which is the actual distance.</p>  

        <p><term>Evaluate</term> a function means to <em>find the value of the output given an input value.</em>  Therefore, evaluate <m>f(2)</m> in our example means <q>Find the train's distance from downtown 2 hours after 8 a.m.</q></p>

        <p>Again, typically we use graphs, tables or formulas to evaluate funtions.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$dist">
                        <static>40</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$miles" category="set">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{feet}</member>
                             <member correct="yes">\text{miles}</member>
                             <member>\text{light years}</member>
                             <member>\text{meters}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $dist= Real(40);
                        $miles = PopUp(["?", "feet", "miles", "light years", "meters"], "miles");
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Remember in a vertical table the inputs are found in the left column (independent variable) while outputs are found in the right column (dependent variable)</p>
                    <table>
                        <tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>t</m> (hours after 8 a.m.)</cell>
                                <cell><m>D = f(t)</m> (miles from downtown)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>10</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>0.5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>12</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>1.5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>20</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>2.5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>40</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>3.0</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>46</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>3.5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>47</m></cell>
                            </row>
                        </tabular>
                    </table>
                    <p>Use the table to evaluate <m>f(2.5)</m></p>
                    <p><m>f(2.5)= </m><var name="$dist" width="5" /> <var name="$miles" form="popup" /></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>In general when the inputs and outputs are nothing in particular, we use <m>x</m> as input and <m>y</m> as output so that <m>y = f(x)</m>.  We use <q>x</q> as symbol to hold a spot for the actual input value while <m>y</m> is a spot holder for whatever the output value will be.  The <m>x</m> basically says, <q>When you get the input, put it here</q> in all the places where the <m>x</m> is.</p>

        <p>Consider the function <m>f(x) = 50x + 10</m>.  The function has no context (no story) so we won't bother using units for either <m>x</m> or <m>y</m>.</p>

        <p>If <m>x = 1</m> then we can evaluate <m>f(1)</m>  by replacing the <q>x</q> in the formula with a 1.  Literally, <m>f(1)</m> means, <q>the formua with a 1 in it</q>.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$output1">
                        <static>10</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$output2">
                        <static>110</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$output3">
                        <static>-5</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$output4">
                        <static>-17</static>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $output1 = Real(10);
                        $output2 = Real(110);
                        $output3 = Real(-5);
                        $output4 = Real(-17);
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Let <m>f(x) = 50x + 10</m>.  Evaluate the expressions below:</p>
                    <p><m>f(0) = </m> <var name="$output1" width="5" /></p>
                    <p><m>f(2) = </m> <var name="$output2" width="5" /></p>
                    <p>Even if the formula changes, we still replace all the <m>x</m>'s in the formula with the given input value.  Try this new funtion <m>f(x) = \frac{x^2+1}{x-5}</m></p>
                    <p><m>f(-8) =</m> <var name="$output3" width="5" /></p>
                    <p><m>f(4) =</m> <var name="$output4" width="5" /></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
        
        <p>According to <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Function_(mathematics)">Wikipedia</url>, a function has the following definition:</p>
                
        <blockquote><q>In mathematics, a function is a relation between a set of inputs and a set of permissible outputs with the property that each input is related to exactly one output.</q></blockquote>

        <p>If you actually read the entire Wikipedia entry you will find the definition of a function can be quite lengthy in order to cover all the universe of mathematics.  In this activity we are going to keep the language simple, informal and we will use some analogies from our train story as examples.</p>
        
        <p>Remebmer this: One input, one output.</p>

        <p>A function is a rule that takes a piece of <q>usable</q> information that you pick and gives you some kind of result.  By <q>usable</q> we mean information that has meaning for the function.  In our train story the only usable information we can choose are times between <m>0</m> and <m>7</m> hours after 8 <abbr>a.m.</abbr> (inclusive).  We have no information about times less than <m>0</m> or greater than <m>7</m> hours after 8 <int>a.m.</int>.</p>

        <p>The most important part is that for each input the function gives you only one result, and each individual input always gives the same single result. This sound terribly confusing, but it makes more sense if we just think about the train.</p>

        <p>For instance, for the train fuction <m>D = f(t)</m> at any given time like <m>t = 2</m> the train can only be in one place.  That's the only result.  It's not possible for the train to be in two or more places (results) at the same time.  Also, every time you put 2 into the function, the train is always in the same place.</p>
        <p>On the other hand it's possible that the train is 30 miles away from downtown at 10 <int>a.m.</int>, let's say on the way out of town.  But then the train is 30 miles away from downtown later in the day (different time) on the back towards downtown.</p>

        <exercise>
            <title>Decide if each situation is possible given the function <m>y = f(x)</m> where <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are just generic variables.</title>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$situation1">
                        <set>
                            <member>\text{no}</member>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{yes}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$situation2">
                        <set>
                            <member correct="yes">\text{yes}</member>
                            <member>\text{no}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $situation1 = RadioButtons(
                            ["yes","no"],
                            1, labels => ["yes","no"],
                            displayLabels => 0
                        );
                        $situation2 = RadioButtons(
                            ["yes","no"],
                             0, labels => ["yes","no"],
                             displayLabels => 0
                        );
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>
                <statement>
                    <p>Is it possible that <m>f(3)=10</m> and <m>f(3) = 17</m>?</p>
                    <p><var name="$situation1" form="buttons" /></p>
                    <p>Is it possible that <m>f(3)=10</m> and <m>f(8) = 10</m>?</p>
                    <p><var name="$situation2" form="buttons" /></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
        <p>When looking at a graph it's easy to tell if the graph is that of a function or not.  Remember the inputs are found along the horizontal axis while the outputs are found along the vertical axis.  The rule is the same: one input, one output.</p>

        <exercise>
          <title>Determine if the graph is a function</title>
          <webwork>
            <setup>
              <var name="$nopass">
                <set>
                  <member>\text{This graph is a function}</member>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This graph is NOT a function}</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <var name="$pass">
                <set>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This graph is a function}</member>
                  <member>\text{This graph is NOT a function}</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <pg-code>
                $nopass = RadioButtons(
                ["This graph is a function","This graph is NOT a function"],
                1, labels => ["This graph is a function","This graph is NOT a function"],displayLabels => 0
                );
                $pass = RadioButtons(
                ["This graph is a function","This graph is NOT a function"],
                0, labels => ["This graph is a function","This graph is NOT a function"],displayLabels => 0
                );
              </pg-code>
            </setup>
            <statement>
              <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/QEW6GNwr/width/431/height/313/border/888888/sri/true" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
              <p><var name="$nopass" form="buttons" /></p>
              <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/NnkVeAwc/width/431/height/313/border/888888/sri/true" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
              <p><var name="$pass" form="buttons" /></p>
            </statement>
          </webwork>
        </exercise>
        
        <p>Tables are another way to express inputs and outputs. In a vertical table the inputs are on the left while the outputs are on the right.  In a horizontal table, the top row is the input and the bottom row is the output.</p>
        <exercise>
          <title>Determine if each table is a function or not</title>
          <webwork>
            <setup>
              <var name="$table1">
                <set>
                  <member>\text{This table is a function}</member>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This table is NOT a function}</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <var name="$table2">
                <set>
                  <member>\text{This table is a function}</member>
                  <member correct="yes">\text{This table is NOT a function}</member>
                </set>
              </var>
              <pg-code>
                $table1 = RadioButtons(
                ["This table is a function","This table is NOT a function"],
                1, labels => ["This table is a function","This table is NOT a function"],displayLabels => 0
                );
                $table2 = RadioButtons(
                ["This table is a function","This table is NOT a function"],
                0, labels => ["This table is a function","This table is NOT a function"],displayLabels => 0
                );
              </pg-code>
            </setup>
            <statement>
              <p>Is the table of values a function or not?</p>
              <table>
                  <tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
                      <col halign="center"/>
                      <col halign="center"/>
                      <row>
                          <cell>5</cell>
                          <cell>8</cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                          <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                          <cell><m>10</m></cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                          <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                          <cell><m>-8</m></cell>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                          <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                          <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                      </row>
                  </tabular>
              </table>
              <p><var name="$table1" form="buttons" /></p>
                  <p>Is the table of values a function or not?</p>
                  <table>
                      <tabular top="medium" bottom="medium" left="medium" right="medium">
                          <col halign="center"/>
                          <col halign="center"/>
                          <row>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                          </row>
                          <row>
                              <cell><m>10</m></cell>
                              <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                          </row>
                          <row>
                              <cell><m>-8</m></cell>
                              <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                          </row>
                          <row>
                              <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                              <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                          </row>
                      </tabular>
                  </table>
              <p><var name="$table2" form="buttons" /></p>
            </statement>
          </webwork>
        </exercise>
        <todo>Insert an exercise to determine if an equation is a function or not.</todo>
        <p>Earlier we mentioned the word <term>evaluate</term>. Again, this means to find the value of the output given an input value.</p>
        <p>But what if the output, the result, is already known and we want to know all the inputs that give us this result?  This is called <term>solve</term>.</p>
        <p>Solve means to work backwards from a known or given output value and determine all the inputs, if any, will give us that output.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$input1">
                        <static>20</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$input2">
                        <static>40</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$input3">
                        <static>60</static>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $input1 = Real(20);
                        $input2 = Real(40);
                        $input3 = Real(60);
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <p>The graph of the function <m>f(x) = (x+4)(x+1)(x-2)*0.1875</m> is shown below.  Use the slider and the manual input box to evaluate each expression.</p>
                    
                    <todo>Question 1.1.10 needs to be finished.  Answers need to be updated.</todo>

                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/bnSUyhHH/width/431/height/313/border/888888" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                    <p>Evaluate <m>f(-4)</m></p>
                    <p><m>f(-4) = </m> <var name="$input1" width="5" /></p>
                    <p>Evaluate <m>f(-1)</m></p>
                    <p><m>f(-1) = </m> <var name="$input2" width="5" /></p>
                    <p>Evaluate <m>f(2)</m></p>
                    <p><m>f(2) = </m> <var name="$input3" width="5" /></p>
                    <p>Use the slider and manual input box to answer these questions about solving.</p>
                    <p>The output on a graph is basically the height of the graph. In general, if <m>x = 2</m> is the input then <m>y = f(2)</m> is the output.  Therefore <m>x = 2</m> tells us where to move left or right along the horizontal axis and <m>f(2)</m> is the height of the graph when <m>x = 2</m>.</p>
                    <p>When you see the sentence <q>Solve the equation <m>f(x) = 4.57</m></q> it means, <q>find all the <m>x</m> values where the graph of the function reaches <m>4.57</m> units high.</q></p>
                    <p>First we must undertand that an equation may have one, many, or infinite or even no solutions. How many solutions does the equation <m>f(x) = 0</m> have?  In other words, how many times is the graph zero units high?</p>
                    <p>Use the slider or the manual input box to determine how many solutions exist for the equation <m>f(x) = 0</m></p>
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
        <p>Notice that each input gives you only one result, so f(x)  is a function.  Also notice that each input has the same output, that's OKAY!</p>

        <p>But, suppose an <q>unknown</q> input value went into the function.  Since we don't know what the input is, we can call it <q>x</q>. Furthermore, suppose we know the output is <m>y = 0</m>.</p>
        <p>In English we could ask the question, <q>What input makes the output equal to 0?</q>  and there would be three answers: <m>x = - 4</m> , <m>- 1</m> and <m>2</m>. All of these values of <m>x</m> give us the same result of <m>y = 0</m>.</p>

        <p>In math we could ask the same question, but it comes out as a statement.</p>
        <blockquote>Solve <m>f(x) = 0</m></blockquote>
        <p>Solve means, <q>Find the input that gives you this result</q>.  In our case the result we want is an output value of <m>0</m>. There are still three answers to the question and each answer is called a <q>solution</q>.</p>
        <p>The statement:</p>
        <blockquote>Solve <m>f(x) = 0</m></blockquote>
        <p>has three solutions:  <m>x = -4</m>, <m>-1</m> and <m>2</m></p>
        <p>On a graph, the output is the height of the graph.  Solve <m>f(x) = 0</m> on a graph means, <q>Find all the places where the graph is zero units high</q>.
        </p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <title>Solving Graphically</title>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$numIntersections">
                        <static>3</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$numSolutions1">
                        <static>2</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$solution1">
                        <static>-2.732</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$solution2">
                        <static>2.464</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$numSolutions2">
                        <static>1</static>
                    </var>                    
                    <var name="$solution3">
                        <static>2.657</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$maxNumSolutions">
                        <static>3</static>
                    </var>
                     <var name="$minNumSolutions">
                        <static>1</static>
                    </var>


                    <pg-code>
                        $numIntersections = Real(3);
                        $numSolutions1 = Real(2);
                        $solution1 = Real(-2.732);
                        $solution2 = Real(2.464);
                        $numSolutions2 = Real(1);
                        $solution3 = Real(2.657);
                        $maxNumSolutions = Real(3);
                        $minNumSolutions = Real(1);

                    </pg-code>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <p>On a graph the output is the height of the graph.  Therefore,<q>Solve <m>f(x) = 0</m></q> on a graph means, <q>Find all the places on the <m>x</m> axis where the graph reaches a height of <m>y = 0</m></q></p>

                    <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/bnSUyhHH/width/431/height/313/border/888888" width="431px" height="313px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
                    <p>To solve the equation <m>f(x) = 0</m> graphically, move the horizontal line to <m>y = 0</m></p>
                    <p>The horizontal line intersects with <m>f(x)</m> <var name="$numIntersections" width="5" /> times</p>
                    <p>You can click on the points where the line intersects with the graph and see the coordinates of the points.  Notice that all the y values are 0, but the x values are diffenent.  The x values are the <em>solutions to the equation <m>f(x) = 0</m></em>.</p>
                    <p>Move the horizontal line to <m>y = 1.9485572</m>. Use this line to solve the equation <m>f(x) = 1.9485572</m></p>
                    <p>How many solutions does the equation have? If there are none, type <q>no solutions</q>.</p>
                    <p>The equation has <var name="$numSolutions1" width="5" /> solutions.</p>
                    <p>Use the coordinates of the intersection points to determine all the solutions to the equation.</p>
                    <p>The solutions are:</p>
                        <p><m>x = </m> <var name="$solution1" width="5" /></p>
                        <p>and</p>
                        <p><m>x = </m> <var name="$solution2" width="5" /></p>
                    <p>Use the slider to adjust the height of the horizontal line and find the solutions to <m>f(x) = 3</m></p>
                    <p>How many solutions does this equation have?</p>
                    <p>There are <var name="$numSolutions2" width="5" /> solutions.</p>
                    <p>The solution is:</p>
                        <p><m>x = </m> <var name="$solution3" width="5" /></p>
                    <p>Suppose the value of y could be anything.  Using the graph and the adjustable horizontal line, What is the maximum number of solutions for the equation <m>f(x) = y</m>?</p>
                    <p>The maximum number of solutions is <var name="$maxNumSolutions" width="5" /> </p>
                    <p>What is the minimum number of solutions for the equation?</p>
                    <p>The minimum number of solutions is <var name="$minNumSolutions" width="5" /> </p>


                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <setup>
                    <var name="$b">
                        <static>0.957</static>
                    </var>
                    
                    <pg-code>
                        $b = Real(0.957);
                        $answer = $b+0.1;
                        $answerevaluator = $answer->cmp(checker => sub {
                           my ($correct,$student,$ansHash) = @_;
                           return (($student > $b)?1:0);
                         });
                    </pg-code>
                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <todo>Insert graph of {2^x} = 0.5x + b with the number b equal to 0.956964. Also need to insert code for conditional questions below. Need to code the no solutions and one solutions parts to this question.</todo>
                    <p>Find a value for b such that the equation</p>
                    <p><me>{2^x} = 0.5x + b</me></p>
                    <p>has two solutions.</p>
                    <p>If b = <var name="$answer" evaluator="$answerevaluator" width="10" /> then the equation would have two solutions.</p>
                    <!-- <p>Find a value for b such that the equation</p>
                    <p><me>{2^x} = 0.5x + b</me></p>
                    <p>has no solutions.</p>
                    <p>If b = <var name="$answer" evaluator="$answerevaluator" width="10" /> then the equation would have no solutions.</p>
                    <p>Find a value for b such that the equation</p>
                    <p><me>{2^x} = 0.5x + b</me></p>
                    <p>has one solution.</p>
                    <p>If b = <var name="$answer" evaluator="$answerevaluator" width="10" /> then the equation would have one solution.</p> -->
                </statement>
            </webwork>
        </exercise>
    </subsection>
</section>
