<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
 
<!-- 
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->

<section xml:id="activity-functions-function-notation" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Function Notation (Input, Output)</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>In this activity we develop an understanding of function notation by comparing statements we already understand in English to equivalent statements written in <q>math</q> language.   We interpret our statements about functions using graphs, tables and formulas.</p>
        <p>There are <m>34</m> questions in this activity.  All questions need to be answered correctly in order for the activity to be complete.  Each question is numbered and is written in bold.  A correct answer will show <q>correct</q> while an incorrect answer will show <q>Try again</q>.</p>
        <p>At the end of the activity you will see how many questions you answered correctly.</p> 
        <p>After completing this lesson you will be able to:
            <ul>
                 <li><p>Interpret the meaning of function notation.</p></li>
                 <li><p>Use function notation to describe an event.</p></li>
                 <li><p>Evaluate a function.</p></li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p>The prerequisites for this lesson are knowing how to read a graph or a table of values and how to use a formula to make a calculation.</p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection>
        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <pg-macros>
                    <macro-file>parserPopUp.pl</macro-file>
                </pg-macros>

                <setup>

                    <var name="$time">
                        <static>2</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$position">
                        <static>30</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$units" category="set">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{miles}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours}</member>
                             <member>\text{miles per hour}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours per mile}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>

                    <pg-code>
                        $time = Real(2);
                        $position = Real(30);
                        $units = PopUp(["?", "miles", "hours", "miles per hour", "hours per mile"], "miles");
                    </pg-code>
            </setup>

            <statement>
                <p>Consider the graph below.</p>

                <p>The dot on the graph represents the position of a train at a particular time. The blue crosshairs represent the time.</p>

                <p>Adjust the time by sliding crosshairs left and right.  Notice that the train's distance, in miles, from downtown depends on the time, in hours, after 8 a.m.</p>

                <p>Without knowing anything about function notation, you can still use a language you already know, English, to describe information about the train.</p>

                <p>For instance:</p>

                <ul>
                    <li><p>The train can only be in one place at any particular time.</p></li> 
                    <li><p>As time passes the train gets farther from downtown.</p></li>
                    <li><p>The speed of the train changes during its trip.</p></li>
                </ul>

                <p>There are also some aspects of the graph itself that you can easily describe in English:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li><p>The graph rises as we read it from left to right.</p></li>
                    <li><p>Sometimes the graph is curved upwards.</p></li>
                    <li><p>Sometimes the graph curves downwards.</p></li>
                    <li><p>Some parts of the graph are steeper than others.</p></li>
                </ul>

                <p>In this lesson we learn to describe situations in math language using function notation.  Later the notation itself will allow us to use math in making calculations.</p>
                <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/D4s2v4ft/width/450/height/459/border/888888/rc/false/ai/false/sdz/false/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/true/ld/false/sri/false/at/auto" width="450px" height="459px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                <p>How far from downtown is the train <m><var name="$time" /></m> hours after 8 a.m.?</p>
                <p><var name="$position" width="5" /> <var name="$units" form="popup" /></p>
            </statement>

            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>In English you can communicate information about time and position in a simple sentence like</p> 

        <blockquote>English:  <q>2 hours after 8 <init>a.m.</init> the train is 30 miles from downtown</q>.</blockquote>  

        <p>Here is what that same sentence looks like in Spanish.</p>

        <blockquote>Spanish:  <q>2 horas despues de las 8 del la mañana el tren esta 30 millas lejos del centro</q>.</blockquote>

        <p>Here is what that same sentence could look like in <q>math</q>.</p>

        <blockquote>Math:  <m>f(2) = 30</m></blockquote>

        <p>The math <q>sentence</q> above is actually an equation and it uses <term>function notation</term> to express the information about the train. Of course, the equation is meaningless unless the reader knows how the notation is defined.  If you know Spanish or <q>math</q> you can <em>interpret</em> the meaning of something you read in those languages into English.  There will be much interpretation in this class.</p>

            <p>In math we use variables and symbols to replace entire words or even entire sentences. For instance, instead of <q>Train's distance in miles from downtown</q> we can use the variable <m>D</m>. Instead of the <q>number of hours after 8 <init>a.m.</init></q>, we can use the variable <m>t</m>.</p>  

            <p>We call the letters <m>D</m> and <m>t</m> variables because they represent values that can change.  Typically we use variables that have something to do with the context of the problem, but sometimes we generalize an expression or equation with <m>x</m>'s and <m>y</m>'s when we have nothing specific in mind.</p>

            <p>If the variables represent actual things or events we must define the varialbles to include the units we used to measure the event. </p> 

            <blockquote>If <m>D</m> is distance you must define the units in which the distance is measured: miles, inches, centimeters, light years<ellipsis />what? </blockquote> 

            <blockquote>If <m>t</m> is time, will it be measured with units of seconds, hours<ellipsis />years?</blockquote>

            <p>Since the position of the train depends on the amount of time that has passed, we say <q>the distance depends on time</q>.  In fact, the distance of the train from downtown is a <term>function of time</term>.</p>  

            <p>Function notation allows us to communicate that distance is a function of time by simply writing <m>D = f(t)</m> [say, <q><m>D</m> equals <m>f</m> of <m>t</m></q>].  Don't confuse the notation with multiplication!  <m>f(t)</m> does <alert>not</alert> mean <m>f</m> times <m>t</m>.</p>

            
        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <pg-macros>
                    <macro-file>parserPopUp.pl</macro-file>
                </pg-macros>

                <setup>

                    <var name="$tarzan">
                        <set>
                            <member>Tarzan times the jungle.</member>
                            <member>Tarzan outside the jungle.</member>
                            <member correct="yes">Tarzan of the jungle.</member>
                            <member>Jungle after Tarzan.</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$helen">
                        <set>
                            <member>Helen loves Troy</member>
                            <member>Helen multiplied by Troy</member>
                            <member>Helen next to Troy</member>
                            <member correct="yes">Helen of Troy</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$f(x)">
                        <set>
                            <member correct="yes">f of x</member>
                            <member>f times x</member>
                            <member>f parentheses x</member>
                            <member>f next to x</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>
                    <pg-code>
                        $tarzan = PopUp(["?","Tarzan times the jungle.","Tarzan outside the jungle.","Tarzan of the jungle.","Jungle after Tarzan."],"Tarzan of the jungle.");
                        $helen = PopUp(["?","Helen loves Troy.","Helen multiplied by Troy.","Helen next to Troy.","Helen of Troy."],"Helen of Troy.");
                        $f(x) = PopUp(["?","f of x.","f times x.","f parentheses x.","f next to x."],"f of x.");
                    </pg-code>

                </setup>

                <statement>
                    <p>How would you say the function notation in each statement below?</p>

                    <ol>
                        <li>Tarzan(the jungle) <var name="$tarzan" form="popup" /></li>
                        <li>Helen(Troy) <var name="$helen" form="popup" /></li>
                        <li><m>f(x)</m> <var name="$f(x)" form="popup" /></li>
                    </ol>
                </statement>

            </webwork>
        </exercise>

        <p>The format of function notation works on the basic principle of input and output.</p> 

        <p>Choose some input, like a time, and the function gives an output like a distance.  The notation tells the reader what the input is by showing it in the parentheses.<me>f(\text{input}) = \mathit{output}</me> In the train problem, the function notation <m>f(0)</m> is telling us the input is <m>0</m>.  The value <m>0</m> in the parentheses means, <q>0 hours after 8 <init>a.m.</init></q>.  In other words it's 8 <init>a.m.</init></p>


        <p><m>f(0)</m> is an output.  It represents <q>the train's distance from downtown, <m>0</m> hours after 8 a.m.</q> Together, the input and output create an <term>ordered pair</term> <m>(0, f(0))</m>.  On a graph the ordered pair is a <term>point</term>.</p>

        <exercise>
            <webwork>
                <pg-macros>
                    <macro-file>parserPopUp.pl</macro-file>
                </pg-macros>

                <setup>

                    <var name="$distance">
                        <static>10</static>
                    </var>
                    <var name="$units" category="set">
                        <set>
                             <member>\text{miles}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours}</member>
                             <member>\text{miles per hour}</member>
                             <member>\text{hours per mile}</member>
                        </set>
                    </var>

                    <pg-code>
                        $distance = Real(10);
                        $units = PopUp(["?", "miles", "hours", "miles per hour", "hours per mile"], "miles");
                    </pg-code>
            </setup>

            <statement>
                <p>The graph below is a function that illustrates a train's distance from downtown, in miles,  as a function of time in hours after 8 a.m.  When using a graph the best you can do is estimate. Since <m>f(0)</m> represents a distance at 8 <init>a.m.</init>, we can use the graph to find what the distance is.</p>

                <p>Move the point onto <m>(0,f(0))</m>.</p>

                <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/P6uUYQqH/width/402/height/499/border/888888/rc/false/ai/false/sdz/false/smb/false/stb/false/stbh/true/ld/false/sri/false/at/auto" width="402px" height="499px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>

                <p><m>f(0)\approx</m> <var name="$distance" width="5" /> <var name="$units" form="popup" /></p>
            </statement>

            </webwork>
        </exercise>



    </subsection>

</section>
