<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->

<chapter xml:id="chapter-combinations-of-functions" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Combinations of Functions</title>
    <introduction>
      <p>In this chapter, we explore particular ways of using two functions together. Etc... </p>
      <list>
        <title>Student Learning Outcomes</title>
        <ul>
          <li><p>Define composite functions and combinations of functions and apply and interpret these in appropriate situations.</p></li>
        </ul>
      </list>
    </introduction>

    <xi:include href="./activity-combination-of-functions.xml" />

    <conclusion>
      <title>Gist of Combinations of Functions</title>
      <p>In this lesson, we learned to <term>combine</term> functions graphically, numerically, and with formulas. However, you most likely have been combining functions at some level your whole life.</p>
      <p>Combining functions means to perform arithmetic operations on the outputs of two or more functions, such as:</p>
      <dl>
        <title></title>
        <li>
          <title><m>f(x) + g(x)</m></title>
          <p>The ouputs of two functions are added together.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <title><m>\frac{\displaystyle{f(x)}}{\displaystyle{g(x)}}</m></title>
          <p>The ouputs of two functions are divided.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <title>Etcetera</title>
        </li>
      </dl>

      <p>Note that this is different from the <term>composition</term> of functions (lesson 08), where the output of one function was used as the input of another function.</p>
      <p>Typical combinations in this course are adding/subtracting and multiplying/dividing functions, though any operation on two or more numbers would correspond to a function combination, <m>f(x)^{\displaystyle{g(x)}}</m> being one example.</p>
      <p>A simple example of the combination of functions is that of <em>Profit</em>, <em>Revenue</em> and <em>Cost</em>.</p>

      <example>
        <p>It costs money to manufacture a product, and you can make money by selling it. The <em>profit</em> is the difference between how much money you collect from selling the product, and how much it cost to manufacture it.</p>
        <p>Let <m>C(u)</m> be the cost, in thousands of dollars, of manufacturing <m>u</m> tons of a product. Let <m>R(u)</m> be the revenue, in thousands of dollars, collected through selling <m>u</m> tons of the product. Finally, <m>P(u)</m> is the profit, in thousands of dollars, from making and selling <m>u</m> tons of the product.</p>
        <p>Using function notation, we would write:<md><mrow>P(u) = R(u) - C(u)</mrow></md></p>
        <p>Work through the following example of this concept.</p>
      </example>

      <exercise>
        <webwork xml:id="profit-and-loss">
          <setup>
            <var name="$profitIsZero"><static>5</static></var>
            <var name="$u1"><static>10</static></var>
            <var name="$u2"><static>4</static></var>
            <var name="$c1"><static>270</static></var>
            <var name="$c2"><static>187.2</static></var>
            <var name="$r1"><static>400</static></var>
            <var name="$r2"><static>160</static></var>
            <var name="$p1"><static>130</static></var>
            <var name="$p2"><static>-27.2</static></var>

            <pg-code>
              $profitIsZero=Real(5);
              $u1=random(6,12,1);
              do{$u2=random(1,4,1)}until($u1!=$u2);
              $c1=-0.8*$u1**2+25*$u1+100;
              $c2=-0.8*$u2**2+25*$u2+100;
              $r1=40*$u1;
              $r2=40*$u2;
              $p1=$r1-$c1;
              $p2=$r2-$c2;
            </pg-code>

          </setup>
          <statement>
            <p>In this problem, remember that Profit = Revenue - Cost, or in function notation:<md><mrow>P(u) = R(u) - C(u)</mrow></md></p>
            <p>The graph below shows the cost function <m>C(u)</m> and the revenue function <m>R(u)</m>. Sliding the given point along the graph of <m>C(u)</m> will also move points on the graphs of <m>R(u)</m> and <m>P(u)</m>, all with the same input values.</p>
            <p>[@MODES(HTML=&gt;'&lt;iframe scrolling="no" src="https://www.geogebra.org/material/iframe/id/YsPBmPHE/width/434/height/440/border/888888/sri/true" width="434px" height="440px" style="border:0px;"&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;', TeX =&gt;"A GeoGebra applet.");@]*</p>
            <p>Notice that the height of the point <m>P(u)</m> is equal to the difference in the heights of points on the <m>R(u)</m> and <m>C(u)</m> graphs.</p>
            <ol>
              <li>
                <p>Move the point along the graph of <m>C(u)</m> until the profit is zero. At approximately how many tons will the profit be zero (give your answer to the nearest whole number)? Note: This value is called the <em>break even</em> point, after which the business begins to make actual profit.</p>
                <p><var name="$profitIsZero" width="5" /> tons</p>
              </li>
              <li>
                  <p>Now click the box to show the graph of <m>P(u)</m>. Notice that it begins with negative outputs, increasing to the break even point, and becoming positive thereafter.</p>
                  <ul>
                    <li>
                      <p>If <m>C(</m><var name="$u1" /><m>) = </m><var name="$c1" /> and <m>R(</m><var name="$u1" /><m>) = </m><var name="$r1" />, then what is <m>P(</m><var name="$u1" /><m>)</m>?</p>
                      <p>Answer: <var name="$p1" width="10" /></p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                      <p>If it costs <var name="$c2" /> thousand dollars to produce <var name="$u2" /> tons, and the revenue is <var name="$r2" /> thousand dollars, then what is <m>P(</m><var name="$u2" /><m>)</m>?</p>
                      <p>Answer: <var name="$p2" width="10" /></p>
                    </li>
                  </ul>
              </li>
            </ol>
          </statement>
          <solution>
            <ol>
              <li><p>The profit is <m>0</m> when approximately <m>5</m> tons of the product are manufactured and sold.</p></li>
              <li><p><m>P(</m><var name="$u1" /><m>) \approx </m> <var name="$p1" /> thousand dollars.</p></li>
              <li><p><m>P(</m><var name="$u2" /><m>) \approx </m> <var name="$p2" /> thousand dollars. A negative profit means the company lost money.</p></li>
            </ol>
          </solution>
        </webwork>
      </exercise>

    </conclusion>
</chapter>
