<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- 
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->

<chapter xml:id="chapter-domain-range-piecewise" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<title>Domain and Range; Piecewise-Defined Functions</title>

<paragraphs><title>Blank Method</title><p>Function notation is a way to tell the reader information about the input and what the output. Again, the way it works is <m>f(input)=output</m>. Whatever is in the parenthesis is the input.</p>
<p>The input can be a simple number like <m>2</m> or <m>-4</m> or the input can be a complicated expression like <m>{x^2} - x</m>.</p>
<p>Your success in this course is almost entirely dependent on your understanding of this simple concept: <em>The <q>blank</q> method.</em></p>
<p>When you see a formula like <m>{x^2} - x</m>. It really means this</p>
<p><m>f(blank) = {\left( {blank} \right)^2} - \left( {blank} \right)</m></p>
<p>At least that's the way formulas really work.</p>
<p>Using this function as an example, <m>f(5)</m> means <q>The formula with a <m>5</m>in it</q>. Literally it means place the number <m>5</m> in all the blanks. As in</p>
<p><m>f(5) = {\left( 5 \right)^2} - \left( 5 \right) = 20</m></p>
<p>The beauty of this is it does NOT matter what you put into the formula (as long as the formula can handle it which we will get into later), the formula does the same thing every time.</p>
<p>You can put <m>5</m> into the formula or you can put something complicated into the formula like <m>\frac{{{x^2}}}{{{x^2} + 1}}</m> which would look like this</p>
<p><m>f\left( {\frac{{{x^2}}}{{{x^2} + 1}}} \right) = {\left( {\frac{{{x^2}}}{{{x^2} + 1}}} \right)^2} - \left( {\frac{{{x^2}}}{{{x^2} + 1}}} \right)</m></p>
<p>Simplifying this equation is another matter.</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs>
	<title>Domain and Range</title>
	<p>Sometimes a formula can only accept certain kinds of values. For instance the square root function <m>f(x) = \sqrt x</m> can only accept values of x are NOT negative.</p>
	<p>In math we say <m>x \geqslant 0</m> meaning the values we choose for <m>x</m> must be greater than or equal to zero.</p>
	<p>The <em>Domain</em> of a function is the set of all the inputs that a function can use. for <m>f(x) = \sqrt x </m> the domain is <m>x \geqslant 0</m> because these are the only values the function can use.</p>
	<p>Another example is <m>f(x) = \frac{x}{{{x^2} - 1}}</m>. In this case the denominator could be zero (a big no-no) if <m>x</m> is either <m>1</m> or <m>-1</m>. So the domain if this function si <q>All numbers except <m>x = 1</m> or <m>x = -1</m></q>.</p>
	<p>An easier way to say the same thing is to state what values you CAN'T use, as in <m>x \ne  \pm 1</m></p>
	<p>For now the only functions that should raise re flags are those that have square roots (because you can't take the square root of negative numbers) and those with deonominators (because we have to avoid any numbers that give us zero in the denominator).</p>
	<p>Once we know what numbers a function can use, we cna then consider what kinds of results we can get. This is called the <em>Range</em> of the function.</p>
	<p>For example, the square root function <m>f(x) = \sqrt {x - 8} </m> has a domain such that <m>x-8</m> must be positive. Therefor the domain is</p>
	<p><m>x - 8 \geqslant 0</m></p>
	<p><m>x \geqslant 8</m></p>
	<p>Under these conditions the function will never yeild negative results.  Only <m>y = 0</m> or positive results will ever come out of this function. Therefore the <em>Range</em>  of <m>f(x)</m> is <m>f(x) \geqslant 0</m></p>
	<p>Domain and Range are often more clear if we look at functions graphically. Below is a graph of <m>f(x) = \sqrt {x - 8}</m></p>

	<example>	    
		<figure xml:id="graph-of-root-x-minus-8">
            <caption>Graph of root function </caption>
            <image>
                <latex-image-code>
                    <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                    \begin{axis}[ymin=-5, ymax=7, xlabel={x}, ylabel={f(x)}, minor xtick={1,2,...,25}, ytick={-5,-4,...,7}, minor ytick={-5,-4,...,7}, xmin=-1, xmax=25, grid=both, axis background/.style={fill=yellow!40}]
                    \addplot[smooth, thick, color=red] coordinates {(8, 0) (9, 1) (12, 2) (17, 3) (24, 4)};
                    \end{axis}
                    \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image-code>
            </image>
        </figure> 
	</example>

	<p>Notice the graph only appears from <m>x = 8</m> and to the right. That's the domain of <m>f(x)</m>.</p>
	<p>Also notice that the graph only appears at or above the <m>x</m>- axis (<m>y = 0</m> or <m>y > 0</m>).  That is the range of <m>f(x)</m> (i.e. range is <m>f(x) \geqslant 0</m>)</p>

</paragraphs>
</chapter>
