<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!--
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->
<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <titlepage>

    <author>
      <personname>Jack Green</personname>
      <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
      <institution>Mt. Hood Community College</institution>
      <email>jack.green@mhcc.edu</email>
    </author>

    <author>
      <personname>Nick Chura</personname>
      <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
      <institution>Mt. Hood Community College</institution>
      <email>nickolas.chura@mhcc.edu</email>
    </author>
    <date><today /></date>
  </titlepage>

  <colophon>

    <copyright>
      <year>2012<ndash />2018</year>
      <holder>Jack Green, Nickolas Chura</holder>
      <minilicense>Creative Commons BY-SA</minilicense>
      <shortlicense>
        This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.
      </shortlicense>
    </copyright>

  </colophon>

  <acknowledgement>
    <p>
      Over several terms, Jack Green wrote most of the book's content as a Word/PDF document for use in his face-to-face and online Precalculus courses at Mt.<nbsp/>Hood Community College.
    </p>

    <p>
      In 2016/2017, Nick Chura, Jack Green and Dr.<nbsp/>Alex Jordan converted the material to PreTeXt (formerly MathBook XML),
      enabling the HTML output alongside a PDF,
      with support from an Open Oregon grant.
    </p>

    <p>
      Special thanks to Dr.<nbsp/>Rob Beezer, David Favreault, Jim Hatton, Robert Hauss,
      Dr.<nbsp/>Alex Jordan,
      Dr.<nbsp/>Elise Lockwood and Gina Shankland for proofreading and review.
    </p>
  </acknowledgement>

  <preface xml:id="to-all">
    <title>To All</title>
    <p>
      Precalculus is taught at Mt.<nbsp/>Hood Community College over two 10-week courses.
      This text aims to address all learning outcomes from the first course,
      suitable for use in a single 10-week term.
    </p>

    <paragraphs>
      <title>HTML and PDF</title>
      <p>
        This text will be released with several synchronous versions that offer different features.
        The essential content of each version is the same as for all others.
      </p>

      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>
              Currently, a preview of the web version is available at <url href="https://www.mhcc.edu/precalc1/"/>.
              The web version offers full walk-through solutions to most exercises,
              as well as interactive elements and easier navigation than print versions.
            </p>
          </li>
<!--
          <li>
            <p>
              A PDF-for-print will be available in June 2017.
              This version is designed to be printed, not read on a screen.
              To save on printing expense, this version is mostly black-and-white.
            </p>
          </li>
-->
        </ul>
      </p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
      <title>Copying Content</title>
      <p>
        Mathematical content can be copied from the HTML version.
        To copy math content into MS Word, <c>right-click</c> or <c>control-click</c> over the math content,
        and click to <c>Show Math As MathML Code</c>.
        Then <c>Copy</c> the resulting code,
        and <c>Paste Special</c> into Word.
        In the Paste Special menu,
        paste it as <c>Unformatted Text</c>.
        To copy math content into <latex/> source, <c>right-click</c> or <c>control-click</c> over the math content,
        and click to <c>Show Math As TeX Commands</c>.
      </p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
      <title>Accessibility</title>
      <p>
        The HTML version is intended to meet or exceed all web accessibility standards.
        If you encounter an accessibility issue,
        please report it to the editor.
      </p>

      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>
              All graphs and images should have meaningful alt text that communicates what a sighted person would see,
              without necessarily giving away anything that is intended to be deduced from the image.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>
              All math content is rendered using MathJax.
              MathJax has a contextual menu that can be accessed in several ways,
              depending on what operating system and browser you are using.
              The most common way is to <c>right-click</c> or <c>control-click</c> on some piece of math content.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>
              In the MathJax contextual menu,
              you may set options for triggering a zoom effect on math content,
              and also by what factor the zoom will be.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>
              If you change the MathJax renderer to MathML, then a screen reader will generally have success verbalizing the math content.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </paragraphs>

    <paragraphs>
      <title>Tablets and Smartphones</title>
      <p>
        PreTeXt documents like this text are
        <q>mobile-friendly</q>.
        The display adapts to whatever screen size or window size you are using.
        A math teacher will always recommend that you do not study from the small screen on a phone,
        but if it's necessary, this text gives you that option.
      </p>
    </paragraphs>
  </preface>

  <preface xml:id="to-the-student">
    <title>To the Student</title>
    <p>
      You may think of this text as a <q>workbook</q>.
      Each chapter begins with activity sets,
      meant to serve as an introduction to a topic,
      and your instructor may assign activities to be done out of class as homework.
      In this way, you will come to class,
      having already studied the basics of a new topic,
      and ready to build on that new knowledge.
    </p>

    <p>
      The activity sets are followed by a <em>Gist</em> section.
      The <em>Gist</em> assumes that you have completed the activities,
      and it provides a retelling of the basic concepts and techniques.
      This will be a good place for you to refer when studying the material for an exam or quiz.
    </p>

    <p>
      Instead of just <em>reading</em> example problems,
      you will get to explore new ideas by working along
      <em>with</em> the examples.
      Most problems in the book allow you to manipulate dynamic graphs and
      receive immediate feedback by submitting your answers through
      <webwork /> online.
    </p>

    <p>
      We wrote this text with students in mind.
      We know how busy the life of a student can be <mdash /> some working full-time jobs,
      some with children to care for,
      often while taking a full load of classes.
      We want this text to serve as a mobile, interactive reference that you
      can take anywhere you have an internet connection.
      Also, we are releasing this for free,
      to help lessen the cost of higher education.
    </p>

    <p>
      We hope you find learning with this book to be an enjoyable and engaging experience!
    </p>
  </preface>

  <preface xml:id="to-the-instructor">
    <title>To the Instructor</title>
    <p>
      This book is a collection of activities <mdash /> a digital workbook <mdash />
      that replaces traditional textbook reading with an interactive,
      guided-lesson approach to learning.
      The workbook covers common topics of precalculus that are otherwise
      delivered as passive reading assignments or lectures.
    </p>

    <p>
      We hope this book will feel very natural to use.
      Each chapter begins with <em>activities</em>
      which introduce students to the basics of a topic.
      Activities use <webwork />, an open-source online homework system, to
      give students immediate feedback on their learning.
      Many exercises include dynamic
      <url href="http://geogebra.org">GeoGebra</url>
      graphs for students to manipulate.
    </p>

    <p>
      These activities mimic what has traditionally been done in discovery-based classroom work,
      to be completed by students as <q>homework</q>.
      Having completed the activities,
      students come to class ready to engage in further discussion and application of the material.
      Since
      <webwork /> gives students immediate feedback,
      they get basic questions answered as they <em>actively read</em>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Following the activities,
      each chapter has a <em>Gist</em>
      section which resembles the expository content in a traditional textbook,
      though it still has interactive components such as found in the activities.
    </p>

    <paragraphs>
      <title>Why Another Math Book</title>
      <p>
        Many mathematics textbooks begin with the assertion that they deliver a <em>new</em>
        or <em>unique</em> approach to learning.
        This book is different, at least in that regard,
        in that the authors concede there is really nothing new in our approach.
        What follows is a presentation of learning that already happens in
        mathematics classrooms worldwide <mdash /> students actively engaged in the learning process:
        experimenting, observing, discovering and applying.
      </p>

      <p>
        Current technology in education software is used mostly in the assessment of homework.
        On the other hand,
        reading material in the form of an e-book is relatively static <mdash /> it is an electronic version of the text that remains a passive reading experience for the student.
        The result is that students often skip the reading altogether and go directly to the homework section where they hope to learn their skills through repetition or by
        <q>reverse engineering</q> the solutions.
        While homework remains a key aspect in student learning,
        it is currently used at the <q>back end</q> of the learning process.
        This text was created with the belief that an active,
        discovery-based approach in knowledge development
        contributes to longer knowledge retention and is linked to a deeper
        understanding of the material.
      </p>

      <p>
        Therefore with this book,
        we hope that the active learning process used so well in college classrooms can be brought to the
        <em>reading</em> experience.
        This is nothing new to mathematics,
        though perhaps it is somewhat new to the textbook.
      </p>
    </paragraphs>
  </preface>

</frontmatter>
