<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- 
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->

<chapter xml:id="chapter-functions" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <title>Functions</title>
    <section xml:id="learning-outcomes-functions">
        <title>Student Learning Outcomes</title>
        <ul>
            <li><p>Identify a function, like from a table of values, a graph or an equation.</p></li>
            <li><p>Recognize, apply, interpret, evaluate and solve equations using function notation.</p></li>
            <li><p>Define a relation and define a function.</p></li>
            <li><p>Perform calculations using function notation including Average Rate of Change.</p></li>
            <li><p>Determine if a variable is dependent or independent.</p></li>
            <li><p>Determine the intervals over which a function is increasing or decreasing or constant based on a numerical, graphical or algebraic model.</p></li>
            <li><p>Demonstrate appropriate use of inequality notation and interval notation.</p></li>
        </ul>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="functions-gist">
        <title>Gist</title>
        <p>A function is a rule that be in the form of a graph or a table of values or a formula.  It may even be a sentence or a set of instructions.  A function takes an input value and uses the rule to create an output value.</p>

        <p>Function notation looks like this: <m>f(\text{input})=\text{output}</m></p>

        <p>But, instead of writing the words <q>input</q> and <q>output</q> we usually use variables, like x and y. Then we define in words what the variables actually mean or represent.  Most often the notation will look something like this: <m>f(x)=y</m>
</p>

        <p>Inside the parentheses is the <term>Independent Variable</term>, like <m>x</m>, and outside the parentheses, on the other side of the equals sign, is the <term>Dependent Variable</term>, like <m>y</m>.</p>

        <example>
            <p>Let <m>E</m> be the fuel efficiency, in miles per gallon, of a car traveling at <m>s</m> miles per hour. For speeds between 5 and 75 miles per hour, the function in <xref ref="speed-vs-efficiency"/> tells us the efficiency of the car.</p>

            <figure xml:id="speed-vs-efficiency">
                <caption>Fuel Economy versus Speed</caption>
                <image>
                    <latex-image-code>
                        <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                        \begin{axis}[ymin=0, ymax=35, xlabel={Speed (mph)}, ylabel={Fuel Economy (mpg)}, minor xtick={5,10,...,75}, ytick={0,10,...,30}, minor ytick={0,5,...,35}, xmin=5, xmax=75, grid=both, axis background/.style={fill=yellow!40}]
                        \addplot[smooth, thick, color=red] coordinates {(5, 11) (10, 19) (15, 24) (20, 26.5) (25, 28) (30,29) (35, 29.5) (40, 30) (55, 30.5) (65,26.5) (70, 25) (75, 24)};
                        \end{axis}
                        \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                    </latex-image-code>
                </image>
            </figure>

            <p>Therefore, the <em>efficiency is a function of the speed</em>. Using function notation we could write an equation saying the same thing: <m>E=f(s)</m></p>

            <p>The input is the speed, <m>s</m>, and the output is the efficiency <m>E</m>. The function <m>f(s)</m> is the graph itself.</p>

            <p>The efficiency of the car is given by the height of the graph.  Therefore <m>f(35) = 28</m> means, <q>The efficiency of the car traveling at <quantity><mag>35</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity> is 28 mpg</q>.</p>
        </example>

        <subsection>
            <title>Inputs have <em>unique</em> outputs</title> 

            <p>An important aspect of functions is that each input can only have one output.  For instance the car can only have one efficiency at a given speed. The cannot get 10 mpg and 20 mpg simultaneously.</p>
  
            <p>However, it is possible there are multiple inputs that give you the same output.  From the graph we see that a fuel efficiency of 25 mpg can be attained by traveling at a speed of about <quantity><mag>20</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity> and also at about <quantity><mag>70</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity>.</p>

        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>Describing functions with intervals</title>

            <p>A function may have many different characteristics. The function may increase or decrease, it may curve up or curve down, it may have positive outputs or negative outputs. When we describe a function, we make our observations relative to the intervals (sections) of the input on which the observation takes place.</p>

            <p>For instance, using our efficiency example, the efficiency may be the lowest at about <quantity><mag>5</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity> and highest at about <quantity><mag>55</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity>. The efficiency increases (goes up) between <quantity><mag>5</mag></quantity> and <quantity><mag>55</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity> then decreases (goes down) for speeds between <quantity><mag>55</mag></quantity> and <quantity><mag>75</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity>.</p>

            <p>Any portion of the speed (horizontal) axis or the efficiency (vertical) axis, is called an interval.  An interval represents a section of the input axis where something special occurs on the function.</p>

            <p>We can use inequalities to describe when the efficiency is increasing, <m>5\lt s\lt55</m>.  This means that fuel efficiency increases for speeds between <quantity><mag>5</mag></quantity> and <quantity><mag>55</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity>.</p>

            <p>Using inequalities we can say the efficiency graph is</p>

            <ul>
                <li><p><term>concave down</term> (bends downwards) for <m>5\lt s\lt60</m>.</p></li>
                <li><p><term>concave up</term> (bends downwards) for <m>60\lt s\lt75</m>.</p></li>
            </ul>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
            <title>Evalueate vs. Solve</title>

            <p><term>Evaluate</term> means to use a known input value to find the output value. Evaluating a function looks like this:</p>

            <me>f(25)</me>

            <p>It means, <q>Find the result of choosing <quantity><mag>25</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity></q>. The symbol <m>f(25)</m> represents an <term>output</term>.</p>

            <p>From the graph we see that <m>f(25)\approx27</m>.</p>

            <p><term>Solve</term> means the output is already known and we are trying to find all the possible inputs that give us the desired result. Solving an equation will look like this:</p>

            <me>\text{Solve }f(s)=25</me>

            <p>In other words it means, <q>Find the input or inputs that give us an output of 25</q>.</p>

            <p>Using our efficiency graph, we can solve the equation <m>f(s)=25</m>.</p>

            <p>At the speeds <quantity><mag>20</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity> and <quantity><mag>70</mag><unit base="mileperhour"/></quantity> the car will have an efficiency of 25 mpg.</p>
        </subsection>

        <exercises>
            <exercise>
                <title>Equation for a Secant Line</title>

                <webwork xml:id="webwork-secant-line">

                    <pg-macros>
                        <macro-file>parserImplicitPlane.pl</macro-file>
                    </pg-macros>

                    <setup>
                        <var name="$a">
                            <static>10</static>
                        </var>
                        <var name="$b">
                            <static>1</static>
                        </var>
                        <var name="$f">
                            <static>\frac{10}{x^2+1}</static>
                        </var>
                        <var name="$x1">
                            <static>1</static>
                        </var>
                        <var name="$x2">
                            <static>3</static>
                        </var>
                        <var name="$y1">
                            <static>5</static>
                        </var>
                        <var name="$y2">
                            <static>1</static>
                        </var>
                        <var name="$slope">
                            <static>2</static>
                        </var>
                        <var name="$line">
                            <static>y=2(x-1)+5</static>
                        </var>

                        <pg-code>
                            Context("ImplicitPlane")->flags->set(reduceConstants=>0);
                            $x1 = Real(1);
                            $x2 = Real(random(3, 5, 1));
                            $b = Real(random(1,3,1));
                            $a = Real(lcm($x1**2+$b,$x2**2+$b))*random(1,3,1);
                            $f = Formula("$a/(x^2+$b)");
                            $y1 = $f->eval(x=>$x1);
                            $y2 = $f->eval(x=>$x2);
                            $Dy = $y2 - $y1;
                            $Dx = $x2 - $x1;
                            $slope = Formula("$Dy/$Dx");
                            $line = Compute("y = $slope*(x - $x1) + $y1");
                        </pg-code>
                    </setup>

                    <statement>
                        <p>Find a formula for the line passing through the function <m>f(x) = <var name="$f"/></m>  at <m>x = <var name="$x1"/></m> and <m>x = <var name="$x2"/></m>.</p>
                        <p><answer var="$line" width="20" /></p>
                    </statement>

                    <solution>
                        <p>Since <m>f(<var name="$x1"/>) = <var name="$y1"/></m>, and <m>f(<var name="$x2"/>) = <var name="$y2"/></m>, then the slope of this line is <m>\frac{<var name="$y2"/> - <var name="$y1"/>}{<var name="$x2"/> - <var name="$x1"/>}=<var name="$slope"/></m>. Using the point-slope form, we can write the line's equation as <m>y=<var name="$slope"/>(x-<var name="$x1"/>)+<var name="$y1"/></m>.</p>
                    </solution>
                </webwork>

            </exercise>
         </exercises>

    </section>

    <xi:include href="./activity-function-notation.xml" />

</chapter>
