<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--
## ********************************************************************* ##
## Copyright 2016                                                        ##
## Jack Green, Nick Chura                                                ##
##                                                                       ##
## This file is part of the Mount Hood Community College                 ##
## Precalculus Project                                                   ##
##                                                                       ##
## ********************************************************************* ##
-->

<chapter xml:id="preface" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<title>Preface</title>
<paragraphs><title>Why another math book</title>
<p>Many textbooks strike a great balance between teaching <em>concepts</em> and <em>computation</em>. They provide excellent examples with real-world data, incorporating current events that appeal to today's student. The only problem is that most students <em>do not read them</em>. <fn>[This <a href="bit.ly/1LppErQ">2011 study</a> found that only 25&#78; completed the reading before coming to class.]</fn></p>
<p>The way students use the textbook often follows this process:
  <ul>
    <li><p>The instructor assigns reading and homework problems.</p></li>
    <li><p>Students skip the reading and begin the homework.</p></li>
    <li><p>If stuck, the student searches for an example like the problem they're working on.</p></li>
  </ul></p>
<p>In this way, the textbook becomes merely a template of problems and solutions to emulate.</p>
<p>Every mathematics textbook begins with the assertion that it delivers a <em>new</em> or <em>unique</em> approach to learning. This book is different, at least in that regard, in that the authors concede there is really nothing <q>new</q> in our approach. What follows is a presentation of learning that happens in mathematics classrooms all over the world <mdash /> students actively engaged in the learning process: experimenting, observing, discovering and applying.</p>
<p>We strongly believe that <em>successful</em> students are <em>active</em> students. They are not merely passively absorbing knowledge, but they are involved in the learning process. To help all students engage the learning process this way, we invite you to learn Precalculus with <em>Active Reading</em>.</p>
<paragraphs><title>What is <em>Active Reading</em></title>
<p>Instead of providing another <em>passive</em> reading experience for our students, we desire to make reading an <em>active</em> one. Each time a concept, definition or technique is introduced, students have an opportunity to practice it right away. Through manipulable graphs and WeBWorK exercises, students are led to discover and apply their knowledge on every page.</p>
<p>In this way, we hope, the active learning process developed so well in college classrooms can be brought to the <em>reading</em> experience. As concepts are introduced, students answer low-stakes questions through WeBWorK, to help develop a basic understanding of new ideas. This is nothing <em>new</em> to mathematics, though it may be <em>new</em> to the textbook.</p></paragraphs>
<paragraphs><title>How to use this book</title>
<p><ul>
  <li><p>For <em>instructors</em>, we hope this book will feel very natural to use. Each chapter begins with <em>activities</em> which introduce students to the basics of a topic. The problems can be assigned, graded and recorded through the use of <a href="http://webwork.maa.org/">WeBWorK</a>, an open-source online homework system.</p>
  <p>These activities mimic what has traditionally been done in discovery-based classroom work, and can be assigned here as <q>homework</q>. Having completed the reading, students come to class ready to engage in further discussion and application of the material. Since WeBWorK gives students immediate feedback, they get basic questions answered as they <em>actively read</em>.</p></li>
  <li><p>For <em>students</em>, you may think of this text as a <q>workbook</q>. Instead of just reading about how a graph moves under function transformations, you will get to explore this by actually moving dynamic GeoGebra graphs. Instead of waiting until class to ask your instructor if you got the problem right or wrong, you'll get immediate feedback by submitting your answers to WeBWorK online. We want this to be a safe learning space and reference that you can take anywhere you have an internet connection. Also, we are releasing this for free, to help lessen the cost of higher ed.</p>
  <p>We wrote this text with students in mind. We know how busy the life of a student can be <mdash /> some working full-time jobs, some with children to care for, some taking <em>too many</em> classes (you know who you are!)</p>
  <p>We really hope you find learning with this book an enjoyable experience!</p>
</li></ul></p>
</paragraphs>
<p>Sincerely,</p>
<p>Jack Green (jack.green@mhcc.edu)</p>
<p>Nick Chura (nickolas.chura@mhcc.edu)</p>
</chapter>
